<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[A Brief] vindication of the Parliamentary proceedings against the late King James II proving that the right of succession to government (by nearness of blood) is not by the law of God or nature, but by politick institution : with several instances of deposing evil princes, shewing, that no prince hath any title originally but by the consent of the people.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29487</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4656</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17719</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12547319</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12547319</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63101</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29487)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63101)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 955:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[A Brief] vindication of the Parliamentary proceedings against the late King James II proving that the right of succession to government (by nearness of blood) is not by the law of God or nature, but by politick institution : with several instances of deposing evil princes, shewing, that no prince hath any title originally but by the consent of the people.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 60, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by Randall Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: closely cropped at top.</note>
                  <note>Head of title taken from p. 1. of text.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Succession.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63101:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>VINDICATION OF THE Parliamentary Proceedings Againſt the Late KING JAMES II PROVING That the Right of Succeſſion to Government (by Nearneſs of Blood) is not by the Law of God or Nature, but by Politick Inſtitution.</p>
            <p>WITH Several Inſtances of Depoſing Evil Princes, Shewing, That no Prince hath any Title Originally, but by the Conſent of the People.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Ad generum Cereris, ſine caede aut ſanguine pauci Deſcendunt Reges, &amp; ſicca morte Tyranni.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Licenſed <hi>July</hi> 20. 1689. <hi>J. Fraſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed and Sold by <hi>Randall Taylor</hi> at <hi>Stationers-H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:63101:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63101:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Should not think it neceſſary to prefix a <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> before this ſmall Treatiſe, eſpecially ſince it handles only Matters of Fact, ſuch as the Judicial Acts of <hi>Commonwealths,</hi> did I not ſuſpect, that ſome Malicious Perſons, whoſe Inclinations and Opinions are hereby thwarted, would brand it with the Name of <hi>Seditious</hi> and <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monarchical;</hi> therefore I ſhall here enter my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation againſt ſuch malicieus Aſperſions, by decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, That nothing herein mentioned has the leaſt deſign to leſſen the Duty and Obedience of Subjects toward their Princes. And I do ſincerely abhor the Principles of thoſe Men, who make ſo little account of their Duty, that upon the leaſt private Diſguſt or Diſcontent, do invent a thouſand Calumnies to the diſcredit of their Prince, without Conſcience
<pb facs="tcp:63101:3"/>or Reaſon, intending only the revenge of private Injuries, and not the publick Good, as they would plauſibly inſinuate.</p>
            <p>Theſe men I take to be ſuch as the Apoſtles S. <hi>Peter</hi> and S. <hi>Jude</hi> ſpake of, when they ſaid, <hi>God knoweth how to reſerve the Wicked unto the day of Judgment, to be there tormented;</hi> but yet much more thoſe which do contemn Domination or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and are bold and liking of themſelves. Nay further, I am of Opinion, That whatſoever a Princes Title be, if once he is ſetled in the Crown, and admitted by the Commonwealth, every man is bound to ſettle his Conſcience to obey him in whatſoever he lawfully Commands, without examination of his Title or Intereſt: For God diſpoſes of Kingdoms, and brings many things to paſs in the Affairs of Princes, by great and extraordinary means; ſo that if we ſhould examine the Titles at this day of all the Princes in Chriſtendom, by the ordinary Rule of private Mens Rights, Succeſſions, or Tenures, we ſhould find ſo many knots and diſſiculties with which they are perplext, that it would be impoſſible to reconcile them.</p>
            <p>And this is my Opinion for true and quiet Obedience; dand yet on the other ſide, I am as far off from the abject and wicked Flatteries of ſuch as affirm Princes to be ſubject to no Law or Limitation, either in Authority, Government, or Succeſſion; as thô by Nature they had been created Kings from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the World; or as thô the Commonwealth bad been made for them, and not they for the Commonwealth; or as thô they had begotten or purchaſed, or given life to the Publick, and not that the Publick had exalted them, or given them their Authority, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Dignity.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:63101:3"/>
            <p>Theſe, and ſuch like, are the abſurd Paradoxes which ſome Men have writ in flattery of Princes, who in my Opinion deſerve no Commendation or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, ſince ſuch Aſſertions deſtroy all Law, Reaſon, Conſcience and Commonwealths; and do bring all to ſuch an abſolute Tyranny as no Realm ever did, or could ſuffer, no not under the Dominion of the <hi>Turk</hi> himſelf at this day, where ſome proportion of Equity is held between the Prince and People, both in Government and Succeſſion, thô nothing near ſo much as in Chriſtian Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>It is therefore the intent of the enſuing Treatiſe to evince, that our Predeceſſors have not been ſuch Slaves to their Kings, as ſome men would perſwade us; and that the Depoſition of King <hi>James,</hi> (grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to be ſo, and waving the advantage of the <hi>Abdication</hi>) is no new and unheard of thing; as we hope to make appear beyond all doubt or exception. For if we can prove, that moſt Chriſtian Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths have (upon juſt and reaſonable Cauſes, and to prevent Tyranny and Oppreſſion) excluded Princes from Reigning, when their Title by Succeſſion was apparent; and alſo Depoſed Evil Princes, when they had lawful poſſeſſion of the Crown. If common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths (I ſay) have in all former Ages exerted this ample and tranſcendent Juriſdiction, what Reaſon imaginable is there why they ſhould not do ſo ſtill; and ſave themſelves from Publick ruin and deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, by reſiſting and removing their evil Heads, whenſoever they are able ſo to do; ſince God hath wonderfully concurred (for the moſt part) with ſuch Judicial Acts of the Commonwealths againſt their Evil Kings, not only in proſpering the ſame, but by giving them alſo ſome notable Succeſſor in place
<pb facs="tcp:63101:4"/>of the Depoſed, thereby both to juſtifie the Fact, and remedy the Fault of the Predeceſſor; as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by the following Examples, and alſo by this laſt of our own Country, where in place of a King, that endeavored nothing ſo much as the utter ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of our ancient and fundamental Laws and Liberties, the extirpation of our Religion, and the ſubjecting us to the unſufferable Toke of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> our Old and Capital Enemies: Inſtead of ſuch a King (I ſay) it has pleaſed God to bleſs us with one (as it were in token of his approbation of our late Proceedings) who deſigns nothing but the univerſal Intereſt and Welfare of the Nation, as is apparent, ſince in ſix Months he has confirm'd and eſtabliſh'd thoſe Laws and Conſtitutions, which his Predeceſſors have been 60 years undermining; who inſtead of ſuſpending Laws, has only ſuſpended his Negative Voice.</p>
            <p>And we may ſend the ſame Meſſage to the late King <hi>James,</hi> which the States of <hi>France</hi> ſent unto <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorain,</hi> after their Election of <hi>Hugh Capet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ard.</hi> lib. 6.</note> and his Excluſion, which <hi>Gerard</hi> the French Hiſtorian records in theſe Words: <hi>Every Man knows (Lord</hi> James,) <hi>that the Crown and Realm of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland <hi>belong'd unto you, according to the ordinary Law of Succeſſion; but yet the very ſame Laws which gave unto you this Right of Dominion, have judg'd you alſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of the ſame, being you have not endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to frame your Life, and govern your People according to the preſcript of thoſe Laws, nor according to the uſe and cuſtom of your Country of</hi> England; <hi>but rather have allyed your ſelf with the French Nation, our old and inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate
<pb facs="tcp:63101:4"/>Enemies, and acquainted your ſelf with their vile and baſe Manners. Wherefore ſeeing you have forſaken and abandon'd the ancient Intereſt of</hi> England, <hi>we have alſo abandon'd and left you, and have choſen the Prince of</hi> Orange <hi>for our King, and this without any ſcruple or prejudice of our Conſciences at all, eſteeming it far better and more juſt to live under</hi> WILLIAM <hi>the preſent poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſour of the Crown, with enjoyment of our ancient Laws, cuſtoms, Priviledges and Liberties, than under you the Inheritour by Propinquity of Blood, in Oppreſſion, ſtrange Cuſtoms, and Cruelty</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the Speech made by Command of the <hi>States</hi> to <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorain,</hi> (the Name and few other Circumſtances only varied) giving their Reaſons why they had excluded him, which in my Opinion are very weighty ones, and ſuch as ought to be conſidered by all Commonwealths before Admiſſion of their Princes: For as thoſe who are to make a Voyage in a Ship upon a dangerous Sea, do not ſo much reſpect, whether the Pilot who is to guide the Stern be the Owner of the Ship or not; but rather whether he's skilful, and likely to bring them ſafely to their deſir'd Haven, or to drown them amongſt the Waves: Even ſo our principal Care ought to be, that we have a good Prince to lead and guide us happily in this way of Civil and Politick Life, which is the end why Princes and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours were appointed.</p>
            <p>It was a wiſe Saying of the Emperour <hi>Valentinian,</hi> viz. <hi>Digna vox eſt Majeſtate regnantis, legibus ſe alligatum fateri;</hi> It is a Speech worthy of the Majeſty of him that Reigus, to confeſs himſelf bound unto the Laws. And the contrary Saying of the Tyrant
<pb facs="tcp:63101:5"/>
               <hi>Caius Caligula</hi> is juſtly deteſted by all Men, who ſaid unto one (as <hi>Suetonius</hi> reports) <hi>Memento mihi omnia, &amp; in omnes licere;</hi> Remember that all things are lawful unto me, and againſt all men without exception.</p>
            <p>Such a King as this is to be reſiſted in all his Illegal Commands, as much as the former (Ruling by Law and Equity) ought with all due ſubmiſſion to be obey'd. And this is ſincerely my meaning, in writing the enſuing Treatiſe; ſo that by giving this Caution, Thope it will not be perverted to any other ſenſe.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63101:5"/>
            <head>A BRIEF VINDICATION OF THE Parliamentary Proceedings AGAINST The Late King JAMES the Second.</head>
            <p>IT is certainly obvious to the meaneſt Capacity, how various and different mens Sentiments are concerning this great and happy Revolution; they who have been ſo injurious to their Country, as to aſſiſt and further the pernicious Deſigns of the late King, cannot but exclaim againſt thoſe who have ſo timely fruſtrated their arbitrary and damnable Devices. Others there are, who have induſtriouſly labour'd to intimate to the late Government, how ſubſervient they would be to its ends, when it would think fit to employ them as Actors in a National Tragedy. It cannot therefore be expected that any thing imaginable can be ſufficient to ſilence the Clamours of ſuch Men, whoſe Opinions are ſtill broader or narrower than their Conſciences, but always ſquaring with their IntereſTs; who endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to deſtroy the Publick Peace, by their oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63101:6"/>to the preſent Government, as they did by their ſubmiſſion to the former.</p>
            <p>For thô it hath been reputed as the Characteriſtick of a good Government, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi quiſquis, quod vellet, ſentit, &amp; quod ſentit, dicere licet;</hi> yet it muſt be taken with due reſtrictions: For as it is unreaſonable and inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to perſecute Men to the utter loſs of their lives and Fortunes, for not obeying the Commands of a Prince, which are notoriouſly repugnant to the known and approved Laws and Conſtitutions of the Nation they live in; ſo it is not convenient for any Government (thô acting by the foundeſt Rules of Policy, and endeavouring to the utmoſt the Publick good and welfare) to permit Incendiaries with an impetuous and unbridled Malice, to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſent their Actions to the People; who eaſily give Credit to the moſt abſur'd Aſſertions, if but plauſibly inſinuated. And like Hereſies in the Church, thô built on the weakeſt Foundations, notwithſtanding the moſt ſolid Reaſons imaginable are apply'd to ſuppreſs them, often ſpread their Contagion ſo univerſally, that they threaten the Peace of the whole Community, and are very rarely ſuppreſt, till the Authors are cruſht by the weight of the Civil Power: So dangerous a thing it is (both to Church and State) to permit Men to broach Opinions publickly, which tend to alienate the Hearts of the Subjects from their Princes.</p>
            <p>It was an uſual thing in the laſt two Reigns, either to ruine ſuch as oppoſed the Court Intriegues by formal Tryals at Law, for <hi>Sham plots</hi> and <hi>Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies,</hi> when the Treaſonable <hi>Words</hi> or <hi>Pamphlets</hi> were for the moſt part ſo evidently true, that it was pity to puniſh the Authors. Another Project was fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63101:6"/>practis'd, which was to buy off ſuch Men who were more than ordindary bold in canvaſing their Deſigns: A thing neceſſary to be uſed by ſuch Princes who would tranſgreſs the Legal limits which have been prefixt to prevent their Exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances, and have reſolv'd to acquire an abſolute and deſpotick Power; thô it be with the hazard of their own, and the Nations downfal, whoſe Deſigns only want diſcovery to be exploded.</p>
            <p>But in this preſent Government, where we are bleſt with a King that deſigns to carry on the true Intereſt of the Nation, (which is apparent by his many large and advantageous Conceſſions to his People, ſince His Acceſſion to the Crown, having in a manner ſuſpended his Negative Voice) there is no need to practiſe the aforeſaid Stratagems; ſeeing he will have as well the Natural, as the Political Strength of the Kingdom, and may ſafely bring ſuch Male Contents to condign Puniſhment. For thoſe Men that either Loſt any thing, or expected to gain any thing by the former Government, will in no wiſe be ſatisfied without having a ſhare in this, which I am perſwaded the King does not intend to grant.</p>
            <p>So that I direct not my Diſcourſe to any of the fore mentioned Men, knowing they will be againſt Reaſon, as often as Reaſon is againſt them: But there are another ſort of Men who highly approve of our Deliverance; but not of the Methods by which it was accompliſh'd. Which is implicitly, thô not in direct Terms, to deſire Effects without their Cauſes; for the <hi>Gordian</hi> Knot is to be Cut, not untyed.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:63101:7"/>
            <p>Now it is expedient to ſatisfie theſe Men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are numerous, and alſo becauſe their Diſguſt ſprings from Conſcience or Inadvertency, and not from Prejudice.</p>
            <p>Firſt then it is obſervable, that many were for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Terms with the late King, and bringing him to a temper more ſuitable and agreeable to our Laws and Conſtitutions. This would have been an admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Project, if we could have obliged our preſent King to return from whence he came, and be always in a readineſs with a ſufficient Fleet and Army to come and aſſiſt us, when the late King ſhould again invade our Properties. Nay, this would not ſerve our turn, unleſs we could entreat the <hi>French</hi> King to lie ſtill with his Fleet, and not obſtruct our <hi>Second Deliverance.</hi> And herein conſiſts the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this Invention, being it requires little leſs than <hi>Impoſſibilities</hi> to ſuſtain it.</p>
            <p>Now one would think, that we above all other People, had ſufficiently experienc'd how uncapable the moſt exquiſite Laws are to defend us from the encroachments of a Prince, whoſe Inclinations per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade their violation, and are abſolutely incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with his Religion: So that if we conſider, how all the Laws were enacted againſt <hi>Papiſts</hi> that could be devis'd or thought neceſſary, were with the greateſt eaſe imaginable eluded and rendred uſeleſs; 'twill be natural to conclude, That the Means we have uſed were the only effectual ones for our Peace and Happineſs, and that one <hi>Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> is enough in an Age.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:63101:7"/>
            <p>Now there are ſome ſuperficial Objections made againſt the Depoſition of the late King, <hi>viz. That many Kings have been privately Aſſaſſinated; but that we hear of none who have been publickly Depoſed by the Juriſdiction of a National Council or Aſſembly, without the Limits of our own Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Anſwer to which I ſhall endeavour to make it appear, That it hath been the practice of all Nations, and at all times, to aſſert their Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction (as we have done) by the Depoſition of Evil Princes, whenever they had the means to effect it. And we may ſafely bid any of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Kingdoms, who have not been in our Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, to caſt the firſt Stone at us.</p>
            <p>Now, as previous to our main deſign, we ſhall lay down this Poſition, (and ſhew our Reaſons for it) <hi>That as Government and Authority in general is from God; ſo the particular Forms and Magiſtrates are left to the Election of the People;</hi> that is, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they'l have <hi>Democracy</hi> which is Popular Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, by the People it ſelf, as <hi>Athens, Thebes,</hi> and many other Cities of <hi>Greece</hi> had in old times; or as the <hi>Cantons</hi> or <hi>Switzers</hi> at this day have; or elſe <hi>Ariſtocracy,</hi> which is the Government of ſome certain Choſen number of the beſt; as the <hi>Romans</hi> many years were govern'd by <hi>Conſuls</hi> and <hi>Senators,</hi> which the States of <hi>Holland</hi> imitate at this day: Or elſe <hi>Monarchy,</hi> which is the Regiment of one, and this of an <hi>Emperour, King, Duke, Earl,</hi> or the like. Theſe particular Forms (I ſay) are not determin'd by God or Nature, as Government in general is; for then they ſhould be all one in all Nations, as the other is, ſeeing God and Nature are one to all; but it is left to every Nation and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63101:8"/>Country to chuſe that Form of Government which they ſhall like beſt, which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> proveth throughout all the ſecond and fourth Books of his <hi>Politicks</hi> very largely; laying down divers kinds of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in his days, as in <hi>Greece,</hi> that of the <hi>Mile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, Lacedemonians, Candians</hi> and others, and ſheweth the Cauſes of their difference, which he attributes to the diverſity of Mens Natures, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, Educations, and other ſuch Cauſes, that inclined them to make Choice of ſuch or ſuch Forms.</p>
            <p>And this might be proved alſo by infinite other Examples, both of Time paſt and preſent, and in all Nations and Countries, which have not had only different Forms of Government the one from the other; but even among themſelves, at one time one Form, and another at other times. For the <hi>Romans</hi> firſt had <hi>Kings,</hi> and after rejecting them for their Evil Government, they choſe <hi>Conſuls,</hi> which were two Governours for every Year, whoſe Authority they limited by a multitude of <hi>Senators,</hi> which were of their Council; and theſe mens Power was reſtrained alſo by adding <hi>Tribunes</hi> of the People; and ſometimes <hi>Dictators,</hi> and finally they came to be governed laſt of all by <hi>Emperours.</hi> The like may be ſaid of <hi>Carthage</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> and many Cities and Commonwealths of <hi>Greece,</hi> which in divers Seaſons, and upon divers Cauſes, have taken different Forms of Government to themſelves.</p>
            <p>The like we ſee in <hi>Europe</hi> at this Day; <hi>Naples</hi> hath a <hi>King</hi> for its Sovereign; <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Pope; Venice</hi> and <hi>Genoua</hi> have <hi>Senators</hi> and <hi>Dukes,</hi> but their <hi>Dukes</hi> have little Authority. <hi>Florence, Mantua, Parma, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbin</hi> and <hi>Savoy</hi> have their <hi>Dukes</hi> only,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63101:8"/>without <hi>Senatours,</hi> and their Power is Abſolute. <hi>Milan</hi> was once a Kingdom, but now a Dukedom. <hi>Burgundy</hi> and <hi>Lorain</hi> had once <hi>Kings,</hi> and after <hi>Dukes,</hi> and now <hi>Kings</hi> again. <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Polonia</hi> were formerly Dukedoms, and now are King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</p>
            <p>The like may be ſaid of <hi>France,</hi> after the expul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the <hi>Romans,</hi> which was firſt a Monarchy, under <hi>Pharamond</hi> their firſt King, and ſo continued for many years under <hi>Clodion, Merovis, Childerik</hi> and <hi>Clodovaeus</hi> their firſt Chriſtian Kings; but after it was divided into four Kingdoms, one of <hi>Paris,</hi> another of <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> the third of <hi>Orleance,</hi> and the fourth of <hi>Metz;</hi> and ſo it continued for many years; but afterwards it was one Monarchy again. <hi>England</hi> alſo was firſt a Monarchy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Britains,</hi> and then a Province under the <hi>Romans,</hi> and after an Heptarchy under the <hi>Saxons,</hi> and now a Monarchy again under the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And all this by Gods permiſſion and approbation, who in token thereof, ſuffered his own Peculiar People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to be under divers manners of Government in divers Times; as firſt under Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob;</hi> then under Captains, as <hi>Moſes, Joſhua,</hi> and the like; then under Judges, as <hi>Othniel, Ehud</hi> and <hi>Gideon;</hi> then under High-Prieſts, as <hi>Ely</hi> and <hi>Samuel;</hi> then under Kings, as <hi>Saul, David,</hi> and the reſt; and then under Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and High-Prieſts again, as <hi>Zorobabel, Judas Machabeus,</hi> and his Brethren, until the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was taken from them, and they brought under the Power of the <hi>Romans.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:63101:9"/>
            <p>Wherefore there can be no doubt, but that the Commonwealth hath power to chuſe their own Form of Government, as alſo to change the ſame upon reaſonable Cauſes, as we ſhall make appear they have done in all Times and Countries; and God no doubt approveth what the Realm deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineth in this Point, for otherwiſe nothing could be certain; for on theſe Changes depend the Titles of all Princes and Potentates from the foundation of the World; and if they ſhould not be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable, we muſt condemn as Illegal the Acts and Juriſdiction of almoſt all the Princes and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours that ever have Reign'd, which were great raſhneſs and folly to do.</p>
            <p>In like manner it is evident, That as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth hath Authority to chuſe and change her Government, ſo hath ſhe alſo to limit the ſame with what Laws and Conditions ſhe pleaſeth; from whence enſueth the diverſity of Power which each of the former Governments had; as the Dukes of <hi>Venice</hi> at this day are for their Lives, (except in certain Caſes, wherein they may be Depoſed;) and thoſe of <hi>Genoua</hi> only for two years, and their Power is very ſmall and much limited, and their Heirs have no Claim or Pretence at all after them to that Dignity, as the Children and next of Kin of other Dukes of <hi>Italy</hi> have, thô in different ſort alſo: For that the Dukedoms of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbin</hi> and <hi>Parma</hi> are limited only to the Heirs Males, and for defect thereof, to return to the Pope or See of <hi>Rome, Florence</hi> and <hi>Mantua</hi> are to return to the Empire for like defects, and not to paſs to the Heirs Female, or next of Kin, as <hi>Savoy</hi> and others do.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:63101:9"/>
            <p>And now if we reſpect God and Nature, as well might all theſe Governments follow one Law, as ſo different; for that neither God nor Nature preſcribeth any of theſe particular Forms, but concurreth with that the Commonwealth appointeth; and ſo it is to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd, That God concur'd as well with <hi>Italy,</hi> when it had but one Prince, as now when it hath ſo many; and the like alſo with <hi>Switzerland,</hi> which once was one Commonwealth under Dukes and Marqueſſes of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and now are divided into Thirteen <hi>Cantons,</hi> under Popular Magiſtrates of their own; and its certain, that God approves of our moſt Gracious Prince King <hi>WILLIAM,</hi> ſince his Election by the People, as he did of the former Princes, while the Commonwealth were contented with them: ſo as when Men talk of a Natural Prince, or Natural Succeſſor (as many times I have heard the Word us'd if it be underſtood of one that is Born in the ſame Realm or Country, and ſo of our own Natural Blood, it hath ſome Senſe, thô he may be good or bad, and none have been worſe or more cruel many times than Home born Princes:) but if it be meant, as thô any Prince had his particular Government or Intereſt to ſucceed by Inſtitution of God or Nature, its ridiculous, for that God or Nature giveth it not, as hath been declared; but the particular Conſtitution of every Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth within it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Now the Government of every Prince is to be reſpected according to the benefit that redounds to the Subject, for whoſe good it was ordain'd; and when the Subjects live well and proſperouſly, are defended and maintained in Peace, Safety and Wealth; when Juſtice is done equally to all Men,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63101:10"/>the Wicked puniſhed, and the Good rewarded; when true Religion is maintain'd, and Vertue promoted; this is that which importeth the Realm and Subjects, and not where, or in what Country the Prince or his Officers were Born, or of what Nation, Language, or Kindred they be; for that as ſoon as he is placed in that Dignity, he becometh a Stranger to me, and it availeth me little whether he be of my Blood and Country, or not. And I may ſay, as the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſaid to <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> who being King <hi>Davids</hi> Grand-Son, and of the Houſe of <hi>Jeſſe,</hi> thought his State aſſured, and ſo might oppreſs the People at his pleaſure; <hi>Quae nobis pars in</hi> David, <hi>vel quae haereditas in filio</hi> Jeſſe? and ſo they left him, and choſe to be under <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> a Stranger.</p>
            <p>For what availed it them that lived in <hi>Spain</hi> under <hi>Peter</hi> the Cruel; or in <hi>England,</hi> under <hi>Richard</hi> the Third, commonly call'd the Tyrant; what did it import them, that thoſe Princes were of their own Country or Blood, ſeeing they did that to them, which a Stranger (thô never ſo barbarous or cruel) would ſcarce have done? As in like manner, What did it import thoſe Noble Families of the <hi>De la Pools, Staffords, Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genets,</hi> and others, deſtroy'd by <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth? What avail'd it to them, that the ſaid King was not only their Country-man, but their near Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man? What profit or commodity was it to <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Woodſtock,</hi> Duke of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> that he lived under King <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, who was his Nephew, or to <hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi> that King <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth was his Brother; when both were diſgrac'd and put to death by them, and loſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63101:10"/>their Lands and Dignities, which perhaps under a ſtrange Prince they might have enjoyed many years? And laſtly, what availeth it to <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> or <hi>England,</hi> that the late King <hi>James</hi> was deſcended of them, and born with us, or to the preſent Queen, that he was her Father, when he endeavour'd utterly to deſtroy the Peace and Tranquility of thoſe Nations, and unnaturally to exclude his Royal Daughter from the Inheritance of theſe Three Kingdoms, to ſet up a ſuſpected Child, to finiſh the Game which he had begun; ſo as we may ſay (as before, <hi>What part have we in</hi> James, <hi>or what Inheritance in the Son of the</hi> Martyr?</p>
            <p>And ſo much for this firſt Point, which is the ground of all the reſt I have to ſay.</p>
            <p>Now ſince we have (as I take it) fully prov'd, That no King or Goverour hath his Intereſt from God or Nature, but from the particular Inſtitutions of the Commonwealth; I ſhall proceed to evince both by Reaſon and Example, that they have Laws and Rules preſcribed by the ſaid Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, by which they are bound to Rule and Govern their People.</p>
            <p>Now I do really believe, that of all other Governments <hi>Monarchy</hi> is the beſt, and leaſt ſubject to the Inconveniences that others are, and that <hi>Popular Governments</hi> are the worſt, and have ſooneſt come to ruine; as may be ſhewed not only by old Examples of <hi>Greece, Aſia</hi> and <hi>Africa,</hi> but alſo many Cities in <hi>Italy,</hi> as <hi>Florence, Bolonia, Siena, Piſa, Arezzo, Spóleto, Perugia, Padua,</hi> and others, which upon the fall or diminution of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire (under which they were before) took unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63101:11"/>Popular Governments, wherein they were toſſed with continual Seditions, Mutinies, and banding of Factions, and could have no end of their Miſeries, until after inſinite Murthers and Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacres, they came in the end under the Monarchy of one Prince, as at this day they remain. So where the Government of <hi>Ariſtocracy</hi> took place, there were perpetual Diviſions among the Senators; as in <hi>Carthage,</hi> which was the Reaſon that Succours were not ſent to their Captain <hi>Hannibal</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> after his ſo great and important Victory at <hi>Canna,</hi> being the preſervation of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, and the loſs of their own. As alſo afterwards, the Emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Diſunion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Senators among themſelves in the Contentions of <hi>Marius</hi> and <hi>Silla,</hi> and of <hi>Pompey</hi> and <hi>Coeſar,</hi> was the occaſion of all their Deſtruction, and of the Commonwealth with them.</p>
            <p>Now if the Prince who governeth alone, and hath Supreme Authority to himſelf, as he reſembles God in this point of ſole Command; ſo could he reſemble him alſo in wiſe, diſcreet and juſt Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in Ruling without Paſſion; Nothing more excellent in the World could be deſired for the perfect Felicity of his Subjects. But becauſe a King is a Man, as others be, and therefore not only ſubject to Errors in Judgment but alſo to paſſionate Aſſections in his Will; therefore it was neceſſary that the Commonwealth, as it gave him this great power over them, ſo it ſhould aſſign him the beſt Helps that might be, for directing and rectifying both his Will and Judgment, and make him as like in Government to God, whom he repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth, as mans Frailty can reach unto.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:63101:11"/>
            <p>For this Conſideration they aſſign'd to him the aſſiſtance and direction of Law; <hi>Which</hi> (<hi>Aristotle</hi> ſaith) <hi>is a certain Mind diſquieted with no diſordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Affection, as mens Minds commonly be; for that when a Law is made, for the moſt part its upon due conſideration, and without perturbation of evil Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as</hi> Anger, Envy, Hatred, Raſhneſs, <hi>or the like Paſſions; and it is referred to ſome good End and Commodity of the Commonwealth; which Law being once made, remaineth ſtill the ſame, without alteration or partial Affection, being indifferent to all, ſpeaking alike to every Man, in which it reſembles the Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of God himſelf.</hi> For which cauſe the ſaid Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſtot.</hi> lib. 3. cap. 12.</note> 
               <hi>That he who joyneth a Law to govern with the Prince, joyneth God to him; but he that joyneth to the Prince his Affections, joyneth a Beaſt: So that a Prince Ruling by Law is more than a Man, or a man Deified; and a Prince Ruling by his Will, is leſs than a Man, or a man Brutified.</hi> In another place the ſame Philoſopher ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſtot.</hi> lib. 1. cap. 2.</note> 
               <hi>That a Prince who leaveth Law, and Ruleth himſelf and others by his Appetite, is of all Creatures the worſt, and of all Beaſts the moſt furious and dangerous: For that nothing is ſo outragious as Injuſtice Arm'd, and no Armour is ſo ſtrong as Wit and Authority; the firſt he hath as Man, the other as a Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For this cauſe all Commonwealths have preſcribed Laws unto their Princes, whereby to govern as by a moſt excellent, certain and immutable Rule; to which ſenſe <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaid, <hi>Leges ſunt inventoe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 2. Offic.</note> 
               <hi>ut omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſemper una, &amp; eadem v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce loquerentur.</hi> For which reaſon they have been called by Philoſophers a <hi>Rule</hi> or <hi>Square</hi> inflexible: But the Prophet <hi>David</hi> (who was alſo a King) ſeemeth to call them by the Name
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63101:12"/>of <hi>Diſcipline;</hi> for that as Diſcipline keeps all the parts of a Man, or of a particular Houſe in order; ſo Law (duly adminiſtred) keeps all the Members of a Commonwealth in Peace and Plenty. And to ſhew how ſeverely God exacteth this at all Princes hands,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note> he uſes theſe Words; <hi>And not learn ye Kings, and be inſtructed ye Princes of the Earth: Serve God in fear, and rejoyce in him with trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling. Embrace the</hi> Diſcipline, <hi>leſt he enter into wrath, and ſo ye periſh from the way of Righteouſneſs.</hi> Which Words being ſpoken by a Prophet and a King, contain many Points worthy of Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</p>
            <p>As firſt, That Kings are pound to learn Law and Diſcipline: Secondly, To obſerve the ſame with great humility and fear of Gods Wrath: And, Thirdly, That if they do not, they ſhall periſh from the way of Righteouſneſs. As if the greateſt Plague imaginable to a Prince were to loſe the Way of Righteouſneſs, Law and Juſtice, in his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to give himſelf over to Paſſion and his own Will, whereby he is ſure to come to Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wreck.</p>
            <p>From like Authority, and for like Conſideration, have come the Limitation of all Kings and Kingly Power, in all Times, and in all Countries, both touching themſelves their Poſterity and Succeſſors. Which is apparent in the two moſt Renowned States of the World, that of the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,</hi> who both began with Kings but yet with far different Laws and Reſtraints about their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities.</p>
            <p>For in <hi>Rome,</hi> the Kings that ſucceeded <hi>Romulus</hi> had great Authority, but yet their Children, or next in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63101:12"/>Blood, ſucceeded them not, unleſs choſen by the Senate and People; ſo as of the Three moſt excellent Kings that enſued immediately after <hi>Romulus,</hi> viz. <hi>Numa Pompilius, Tullius Hoſtilius,</hi> and <hi>Tarquinus Priſcus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit. Liv.</hi> lib. 1. doe. 1.</note> none of them were of the Blood Royal, nor of Kin to one another, nor yet <hi>Romans</hi> born; but choſen rather from amongſt Strangers, for their Vertue and Valour. In <hi>Greece,</hi> among the <hi>Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monians,</hi> which was the moſt eminent Kingdom at that time, the Succeſſion of Children was moſt certain; but yet their Power was ſo reſtrain'd by the <hi>Ephori,</hi> as they were not only checked and chaſtned by them, if occaſion ſerved, but alſo De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived, and ſometimes put to Death. For this Cauſe <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> did juſtly miſlike this eminent Juriſdiction of the <hi>Ephori</hi> over their Kings; but yet we ſee hereby what Authority the Commonwealth had in this caſe, and what their meaning was in making Laws, and reſtraining their Kings Power, <hi>viz.</hi> thereby the more to bind them to do Juſtice.</p>
            <p>We may repeat a multitude of ſuch Examples in Heathen Kingdoms, but being they may be rejected, as being no Preſident for us, we ſhall haſte to ſhew, How Chriſtian Kingdoms have limited their Princes.</p>
            <p>Now, if we conſider the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire as it is at this day annexed to the <hi>German</hi> Electors; thô it be the firſt in Dignity amongſt Chriſtian Princes, yet we ſhall ſee it ſo reſtrained by particular Laws, as the Emperour cannot do ſo much as other Kings; for he can neither make War, nor exact any Mony but by the free leave and conſent of the <hi>German</hi> Dyer or Parliament; and as for his Children, or next of Kin, they have no Intereſt or Pretence to ſucceed in their Fathers Dignity, but only by free Election,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63101:13"/>if they ſhall be thought worthy. Nay, one of the chiefeſt Points that the Emperour muſt Swear at his Entrance is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sleyden,</hi> lib. 8.</note> That he will never go about to make the Dignity of the Empire Peculiar or Hereditary to his Family, but leave it to the Electors (free in their power) to chuſe his Succeſſor, according to the Law made by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Fifth, and the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the Fourth.</p>
            <p>The Kingdom of <hi>Polonia</hi> is much of the ſame manner with the Empire, both for its reſtraint of Power,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cromenias,</hi> lib. 3. hiſt. <hi>Polo.</hi>
               </note> and ſucceſſions of its King, for they have great Limitations, being they can do nothing of great moment without the conſent of certain Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Officers, called <hi>Palatines</hi> or <hi>Caſtellans;</hi> neither may their Children ſucceed them, unleſs they are Choſen; as in the Empire, in <hi>Spain, France</hi> and <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the Priviledges of Kings is much different from the former.</p>
            <p>The Kings of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>France</hi> have greater Power than the Kings of <hi>England;</hi> for that every Ordination of theſe two Kings is Law it ſelf, without the Approbation of the Commonwealth: But in the Point of Succeſſion it appeareth, that the reſtraint is far greater in thoſe two Countreys than in <hi>England;</hi> for in <hi>Spain</hi> the next of Blood cannot ſucceed but by a new Approbation of the Nobility and Biſhops of the Realm, as it is expreſly ſet down in the two Ancient Councils of <hi>Toledo</hi> the <hi>4th</hi> and <hi>5th.</hi> In <hi>France</hi> the World knows, that Women are not admitted to ſucceed in the Crown, be they never ſo near in Blood, neither any of their Iſſue, thô it be Male. For which cauſe <hi>Edward</hi> the Third of <hi>England,</hi> thô he were Son and Heir to the Daughter of <hi>France,</hi> whoſe three Brothers were
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63101:13"/>Kings, and left her ſole Heir to her Father <hi>Philip</hi> the Fourth, yet was he put by the Crown, and <hi>Philip de Valois,</hi> a Brothers Son of <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>4th</hi> preferr'd to it by general Conſent of the whole Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>Paris.</hi> And thô the <hi>Salic</hi> Law is not very ancient, as the <hi>French</hi> themſelves do confeſs, and much leſs made by <hi>Pharamond</hi> their firſt King, or in thoſe ancient Times, as ſome without ground do affirm; yet we ſee its ſufficient to bind all Princes and Subjects of that Realm to obſerve the ſame, and alter the courſe of Natural Deſcent and Nearneſs of Blood, as we have ſeen; but ſuch things are not ſuffered in <hi>England,</hi> for that our Laws are otherwiſe, which were made by the Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>By all which it is manifeſt, that moſt Kingdoms have different Laws and Cuſtoms, both as to their Authority and Succeſſion; and it is not enough for a man to alledge bare propinquity of Blood, for that he may be excluded for ſeveral other Reaſons, which we ſhall hereafter diſcuſs.</p>
            <p>I know it hath been confidently aſſerted by ſome baſe Flatterers, that in all ſucceſſive Monarchs the Heir ſhould enter by title of Birth, without condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, conſent, or approbation of the Realm; as alſo without Coronation Oath, or Obligation to fulfil any Law, or to obſerve any Priviledges of Church or State. Theſe are things which only ſerve to ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſie the People, and ſet them more againſt his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, than to advance his Title.</p>
            <p>Another of their Propoſitions is, That albeit the Heir apparent, which is next by Birth to any Crown, ſhould be never ſo impotent or unfit to govern; or if it ſhould be known, that he were moſt Malicious and Wicked, and ſhould go about to deſtroy the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63101:14"/>Commonwealth, and drown the Ship he had to guide; yet (ſay they) he muſt be Sacred, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted without contradiction to his Inheritance, which God and Nature hath deſigned him, and his direction, reſtraint or puniſhment, muſt only be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to God alone; for that no Man or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth may reform or reſtrain him.</p>
            <p>This Doctrin (one would think) ſhould be no ſooner delivered, but contemn'd by any Rational man, who regards the end why all Commonwealths and Kingdoms, and all Governments were ordained by God and Nature, and not the flattering or adoring of any one miſerable Man, who ſhall endeavour to deſtroy the whole.</p>
            <p>But to come to the particular Matter we are to treat of, which is, What is to be attributed to Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion or Propinquity of Birth alone?</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore, I am perſwaded that Succeſſion is much to be preferred, not for that it wanteth all all Difficulties and Inconveniences; but like as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I have ſhewed of the particular Government of Monarchy in reſpect of other Forms, <hi>viz.</hi> that it wanted not all, but had ſewer Inconveniences than other Forms of Regiment have; ſo I ſay alſo of this, That thô ſome Inconveniences are not wanting in Succeſſion; yet they are commenly far leſs and fewer, than would follow by meer Election, which is ſubject to great and continual danger of Ambition, Emulation, Diviſion and Sedition, which do evidently threaten the univerſal deſtruction and deſolation of the whole Body at the Death of every Prince, which Inconveniences have no place in Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Prince who is in preſent poſſeſſion,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63101:14"/>knowing that his Son or next of Kin is to ſucceed, takes care to leave the Realm in good order; as the Husbandman doth to Till and Manure the Ground, which is his own, and muſt remain to his Poſterity.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, There are leſs alterations in Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths where Succeſſion prevails, for that the Son commonly retains the ſame Friends, Counſellors and Officers which his Father had before him, and often purſues the ſame Actions and Intentions.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, He that entreth by Succeſſion is either born a Prince, or hath been much reſpected for his Title to the Crown, and bringeth leſs Paſſions of Hatred, Emulation, Anger, Envy or Revenge againſt particular Men, (for that no man durſt offend him) than he who entreth only by Election; for he having been a Subject and equal to others before his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement, and therefore had contention with many, eſpecially about his Election, which he will ſeek to revenge when he is in Authority. As on the other ſide alſo, ſuch as were his Equals before will bear him leſs reſpect, and be more unwilling to obey him, than if by Birth he had been their Sovereign.</p>
            <p>Now as by Succeſſion we remedy the difficulties of Election, yet there remains one great and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Inconveniency in the former; namely. That ſome unapt, impotent or evil Prince may offer to enter by priority of Blood, which is to be prevented by adding Election, Conſent and Approbation of the Realm to Succeſſion, ſo as Succeſſion by Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and Election by Succeſſion will be help'd, and the one made a Preſervative and Remedy againſt the other. And this is the wiſdom and high Policy left by God and Nature to every Commonwealth, for their own Conſervation and Maintenance, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63101:15"/>every Man that is void of Paſſion, will not only allow, but alſo commend the ſame.</p>
            <p>Now we ſhall proceed and ſhew what Intereſt a Prince hath before he's Crown'd or Admitted by the Realm, which I take to be the ſame as the King of the <hi>Romans</hi> hath to the <hi>German</hi> Empire, after his Election, and before he is Crown'd Or to uſe a more familiar Example to Engliſhmen as the Mayor of <hi>London</hi> hath to the Majoralty, after he is Choſen, and before he is admitted or taken his Oath. For as this Man in rigour is not truly Mayor, nor hath his Juriſdiction before his Oath and Admiſſion, nor the other properly Emperour before his Coronation; ſo is not the Heir truly King, though his Predeceſſor be dead, and he next in Succeſſion, until he is Crown'd or Admitted by the Commonwealth; thô for better keeping of Order, and avoiding Tumults and Conſuſion, moſt Commonwealths that have their Princes by Succeſſion, have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, that from the Death of the former Frinces all Matters of Government ſhall paſs in the Name of the Succeſſor, (if his Succeſſion be clear under ſuppoſition of the Confirmation and Approbation of the Commonwealth afterwards.</p>
            <p>Now as for the Princes of <hi>England,</hi> it's expreſly noted by Engliſh Hiſtorians, that it only hapned to <hi>Henry</hi> the Fifth, among all his Predeceſſors, to have Homage done unto him before his Coronation and oath taken, and that for the exceeding Love and Affection the People had for him. Whereof <hi>Polydore</hi> writeth in theſe words:<note place="margin">Polydor. Virgil <hi>lib. 22.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Prince</hi> Henry, <hi>after he had finiſht his Fathers Funeral, cauſed a Parliament to be conven'd at</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>where whilſt Conſultation was had according to the ancient
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63101:15"/>Cuſtom of</hi> England, <hi>about Creating a new King; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold on a ſudden certain of the Nobility of their own free wills began to Swear Obedience and Loyalty to him: Which demonſtration of love and good will was never ſhewed to any Prince before, until he was declared King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Stow</hi> expreſſeth the ſame thing in his Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stow</hi> in the beginning of the Life of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>5th</hi>
               </note> in theſe words; <hi>To this Noble Prince, by aſſent of the Realm, the Nobles after three days offered to do Fealty before he was Crown'd, or had ſolemniz'd his Oath, well and juſtly to govern the Commonwealth; which Offer before was never found to be made to any Prince of</hi> England. Thus much <hi>Stow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In whoſe Narration, as alſo in that of <hi>Polydore,</hi> it may be noted, that King <hi>Henry</hi> was not called King till after his Coronation, thô his Father had been dead almoſt a Month before: As ſecondly, That the Parliament conſulted about making a new King, according to the Cuſtom of their Anceſtors; which argueth that he was not yet King, thô his Father was dead; and that the manner of our Old Engliſh Anceſtors was not to account him ſo before his Admiſſion. Thirdly, That this good Will of the Nobility, to acknowledge him for King before his Coronation and Oath ſolemniz'd, truly and juſtly to govern the Realm, was very extraordinary and meer kindneſs. And laſtly, That it was never done to any Prince before <hi>Henry</hi> the Fifth. All which Points do demonſtrate, that it's the Coronation and Admiſſion that makes a true and perfect King, let the Title by Succeſſion be what it will; and that the Conſent of the Realm is of much greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence than nearneſs of Blood.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:63101:16"/>
            <p>This may be prov'd by many Examples in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> where Admiſſion has prevail'd againſt Right of Succeſſion, as in <hi>William Rufus,</hi> who ſucceeded the Conquerour, and King <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in King <hi>Stephen,</hi> King <hi>John</hi> and others, who only by Admiſſion of the Realm were Kings againſt the order of Succeſſion. To theſe we may add <hi>Henry</hi> and <hi>Edward,</hi> both Sirnamed the Fourth, whoſe Entrances to the Crown, if we well conſider, we ſhall find that both of them founded the beſt and ſureſt part of their Titles upon the Election and Conſent of the People: And both of them having Remorſe of Conſcience at their dying days, being they put ſo many Men to death for maintenance of their Rights and Titles, had no better way to appeaſe their own Minds, but by thinking they were plac'd on the Throne by the Voice of the Realm, and conſequently might lawfully defend the ſame, and puniſh ſuch as intended to deprive them.</p>
            <p>Moreover, if we look into the Actions of Princes in all Ages, we ſhall find that ſuch Kings as were moſt politick, and had the leaſt doubt or ſuſpicion of Troubles about the Title after their Deaths, have cauſed their Sons to be Crown'd in their own days, as truſting more to that, than to their Title by Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, thô they were never ſo lawfully and lineally deſcended. And of this I could alledge many Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples out of divers Countreys, but ſpecially in <hi>France,</hi> ſince the laſt Line of <hi>Capetus</hi> came to that Crown; for <hi>Hugh Capetus</hi> himſelf procured <hi>Robert</hi> his eldeſt Son to be Crown'd in his own days and <hi>Robert</hi> did the ſame for his youngeſt Son <hi>Henry. Henry</hi> alſo did entreat the States of <hi>France</hi> to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63101:16"/>Admit and Crown <hi>Philip</hi> the Firſt, his eldeſt Son, in his own time; and this Kings Son <hi>Lewis</hi> did the ſame to both his Sons, firſt to <hi>Philip,</hi> and after his death to <hi>Lewis</hi> the younger. And for the ſame cauſe, the Prince of <hi>Spain</hi> is Swore and admitted by the Realm, during his Fachers Reign. The ſame Conſideration alſo moved King <hi>David,</hi> to Crown his Son <hi>Solomon</hi> in his own days.</p>
            <p>And finally our King <hi>Henry</hi> the Second of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> conſidering the alteration the Realm had made in admitting King <hi>Stephen</hi> before him, againſt the order of Lineal Succeſſion; and fearing the like might happen after him, cauſed his eldeſt Son <hi>Henry</hi> to be Crowned in his life time: But this Device had but ill ſucceſs, for King <hi>Henry</hi> the younger made War upon King <hi>Henry</hi> the elder, and got both the Kings of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and many Nobles both of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Normandy</hi> to take his part; for which cauſe 'tis probable, that this thing has never ſince that time been us'd in <hi>England.</hi> But yet hereby its evident, what the Opinion of the World was in thoſe days of the force of Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Admiſſion of the Commonwealth, and how little the propinquity of Blood prevailed without it.</p>
            <p>I might bring inſinite Examples from the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> to this purpoſe; but that it may be ojbected, that they are too old and far fetch'd Examples, and ought not to be Preſidents to us in theſe Ages. Wherefore I ſhall only give ſome few Examples of the <hi>Jews,</hi> being they were Gods Elect People, and ſo fit Preſidents for us to follow, and then haſten to thoſe of kiter Times.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:63101:17"/>
            <p>Firſt, then Thô God made <hi>Saul</hi> a true and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful King, and conſequently gave him all the Kingly Priviledges, Benefits and Prerogatives belonging to that degree and ſtate; whereof one was, That his Children ſhould ſucceed after him in the Crown; yet after his death, God ſuffered not any of his Generation to ſucceed him, tho' he left behind a numerous Iſſue; and among others, <hi>Iſhboſheth</hi> a Prince of 40 yeras old, whom <hi>Abner</hi> the General Captain of that Nation follow'd for a time as their lawful Lord and Maſter by Succeſſion, until God check'd them for it, and induc'd them to reject him, and to receive <hi>David,</hi> newly elected King, who was a Stranger by Birth, and no Kin to the King deceaſed.</p>
            <p>Now if any one ſhall ſay, that it was for the Sin of <hi>Saul,</hi> whom God had rejected, I do confeſ; it, and yet it makes nothing againſt our purpoſe, being we do not pretend that a Prince, who is next in Blood, can juſtly be put back, unleſs for his own defects, or thoſe of his Anceſtors. And it's to be noted, That <hi>Jonathan</hi> (who was a good Man, and much praiſed in Holy Writ) being ſlain in the Battle, and leaving a Son named <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> who was alſo put back, tho'b y neareſs of Blood he had great intereſt in the Succeſſion, and much before <hi>David,</hi> and that only (for ought appears) upon the account of <hi>Saul</hi> his Grandfather.</p>
            <p>After <hi>David</hi> ſucceeded <hi>Solomon,</hi> who was his younger and tenth Son, and the fourth only by <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> tho' <hi>Adonijah</hi> the Heir apparent, ſeeing his Father old and ready to dye, had call'd many of the great Men of that State, both Spiritual and Temporal, intending to have proclaimed himſelf
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63101:17"/>Heir apparent to the Crown; but <hi>Bathſheba</hi> and <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet coming to the old King, as he lay on his Bed, put him in mind of his Promiſe to <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> made for preferring of her Son; telling him, (which pleaſed him well) <hi>Quod occuli totius</hi> Iſrael <hi>in eum reſpicerent, ut indicaret eis, quis ſederet in ſolio ſuo poſt ipſum.</hi> Which was as much as to ſay, <hi>That the whole Commonewealth referr'd it to his choice, which of his Sons ſhould Reign after him.</hi> Upon theſe Reaſons and Perſwaſions the old King was content they ſhould take <hi>Solomon</hi> out of hand, and put him on the Kings own Mule, and carry him about the Streets of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> accompanied with his Guards, and crying with found of Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, <hi>Long live King</hi> Solomon.</p>
            <p>Hereby we may learn, That theſe and the like determinations of the People, about admitting or refuſing of Princes, to Reign or not to Reign over them, when their Deſigns are to good Ends, and for juſt Reſpects and Cauſes, are allowed alſo by God, and many times are his own ſpecial Drifts and Diſpoſitions, thô they ſeem to come from Man.</p>
            <p>Whereof there can be no more evident Proof, than that which enſued afterwards to Prince <hi>Reho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi> the lawful Son and Heir to King <hi>Solomon,</hi> who refuſing to take away ſome hard and heavy Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, laid on the People by <hi>Solomon</hi> his Father, loſt ten of the twelve Tribes, who refuſed to admit him for their King; but choſe rather one <hi>Jeroboam</hi> that was a meer Stranger, and God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed thereof,<note place="margin">1 King. 12.21.</note> as the Scripture in expreſs words teſtifies: For when <hi>Rehoboam</hi> took himſelf to be openly injur'd, would by Arms have purſu'd his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63101:18"/>Title, and had gathered an Hundred and fourſcore Thouſand choſen Souldiers to reduce the Rebels (as he called them) to their Obedience. God appeared to one <hi>Semia,</hi> an holy Man, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to go to the Camp of <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> and tell them, that they ſhould not fight againſt their Brethren, who had choſen another King, but that every Man ſhould go to his Houſe, and live quietly under the King they had choſen, and ſo they did; and this was the end of that Tumult which God for the Sins of <hi>Solomon</hi> had permitted and allowed of.</p>
            <p>And thus much I thought good to relate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Jewiſh Commonwealth, for that it may give light to all the reſt I am to treat of; for if God permitted and allowed this in his own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monweal, that was to be the Example and Pattern of all others that ſhould enſue, no doubt but he approveth alſo the ſame in other Realms, when juſt occaſion offers, either for his Service, the good of the People, or for the puniſhment of the Sins and Wickedneſs of ſome Princes, that the Line of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion ſhould be altered.</p>
            <p>Now then, to paſs on further, and to begin with the Kingdom of <hi>Spain;</hi> which hath had three or four Races or Deſcents of Kings, as <hi>France</hi> alſo and <hi>England</hi> have had;<note place="margin">Firſt Race.</note> And the firſt Race was from the <hi>Goths,</hi> which began their Reign in <hi>Spain</hi> after the expulſion of the <hi>Romans,</hi> about the year of <hi>Chriſt</hi> 416, to whom the <hi>Spaniard</hi> referreth all his Nobility, as the <hi>French</hi> doth to the <hi>German Franks,</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to the <hi>Saxons,</hi> who entred <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England</hi> in the ſame Age, as the others did <hi>Spain;</hi> and the Race of the <hi>Gothiſh,</hi> Kings endured
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63101:18"/>Three hundred years, until <hi>Spain</hi> was loſt unto the <hi>Moors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Race is from <hi>Don Pelago,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Second Race.</note> that was choſen firſt King of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> after the deſtruction of the Kingdom by the <hi>Moors,</hi> about the year of <hi>Chriſt</hi> 717; which Race continued, and added Kingdom unto Kingdom for the ſpace of Three hundred years, until the year of <hi>Chriſt</hi> 1034, when <hi>Don Sancho,</hi> King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> got the Earl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Aragon</hi> and <hi>Caſtile,</hi> and made them King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, dividing them among his Children, to his ſecond Son <hi>Don Ferdinando,</hi> Sirnamed afterwards <hi>The Great;</hi> he gave not only the Earldom of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilia,</hi> but by Marrying alſo the Siſter of <hi>don Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mudo,</hi> King of <hi>Leon</hi> and <hi>Aſturia,</hi> he joyned all thoſe Kingdoms together;<note place="margin">Third Race.</note> and ſo from that Day began the third Race of the Kings of <hi>Navarre</hi> to Reign in <hi>Caſtile,</hi> and ſo endured for Five hundred years, until the year of <hi>Chriſt</hi> 1540; when the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> entred to Reign by Marriage of the Daughter of <hi>Don Ferndinando,</hi> Sirnamed <hi>The Catholick;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fourth Race.</note> and this was the fourth Race of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Kings after the <hi>Romans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in theſe four Ranks of Regal Deſcents, divers Examples may be alledged for my purpoſe; yet I ſhall paſs by my firſt Race, for that its evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by the Councils of <hi>Toledo,</hi> which were held in thoſe Times, That expreſs Election was joyned with Succeſſion; for in the <hi>4th</hi> Council of <hi>Toledo, Cap.</hi> 74. are theſe Words, <hi>Let no man among us ſnatch the Kingdom by preſumption; but the former King being dead, let the Nobility of the Kingdom, together with the Prieſts and Clergy, appoint the Succeſſour of the Kingdom by Common Council.</hi> Which
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:63101:19"/>is as much as if they had ſaid, <hi>Let no man enter upon the Kingdom by preſumption of Succeſſion alone; but let the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Voice, ſee what's beſt for the Weal-publick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Don Pylao</hi> (the firſt King after the deſtruction of the Kingdom by the <hi>Moors</hi>) died, and left a Son named <hi>Don Favilla,</hi> who was King after his Father, and Reigned two years, aftes whoſe Death none of his Children werre admitted for King, thô he left many; but <hi>Don Alonſo</hi> was choſen by the unanimous Conſent of the <hi>Gothiſh</hi> Nation; and for no other Reaſon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ambro. Moral.</hi> lib. 13. cap. 6. 9. 10.</note> but that the Kings Sons were young and unable to govern; and this <hi>Alonſo</hi> proved an excellent King, and as <hi>Sebaſtianus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salamancha</hi> (who lived in the ſame time) writes, was for his Valiant Acts Sirnamed <hi>The Great.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this Famous <hi>Don Alonſo</hi> ſucceeded his Son <hi>Don Fruela,</hi> who was a Noble King for Ten years, and had many great Victories over the <hi>Moors;</hi> but after declining to Tyranny, he became odious to his Subjects, and was Depoſed and put to Death <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 768;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Moral.</hi> l. 13. cap. 17.</note> and tho' he left two Sons, yet for the Prejudice conceived againſt their Father, neither of them were admitted by the Realm to ſucceed him; but rather his Couſin <hi>Don Aurelio,</hi> who Reigned Six years, and died without Iſſue; and becauſe the Hatred which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived againſt the Memory of <hi>Don Fruela</hi> was not yet extinguiſh'd, they would not yet admit any of his Generation, but excluded them a ſecond time, and choſe <hi>Don Silo,</hi> a Brother-in-Law of his; ſo that the right Heirs of <hi>Don Fruela</hi> were twice put back for his evil Government.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:63101:19"/>
            <p>But <hi>Don Silo</hi> being dead without Iſſue, as alſo <hi>Don Aurelio</hi> was before him, and the Anger of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> againſt <hi>Fruela</hi> being well aſſwaged, they admitted his Son <hi>Don Alonſo,</hi> whom they had twice put back: But he dying without Iſſue, <hi>Don Ramiro</hi> his Couſin was choſen;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Moral.</hi> cap. 33.</note> and thô <hi>Don Ramiro</hi> was next in Blood to <hi>Alonſo,</hi> yet he was elected by the States, as the Hiſtorian expreſly writes.</p>
            <p>But in the time of <hi>Don Ramiro,</hi> the Law of Succeſſion by propinquity of Blood, was much reviv'd and ſtrongly confirm'd, and from this time forward the King always caus'd his eldeſt Son to be named <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Prince,</hi> and to be always Sworn by the Realm and Nobility; yet we ſhall find this Ordinance to have been frequently broken upon ſeveral Conſiderations. As for Example, after ſome Deſcents from <hi>Don Ramiro,</hi> which were <hi>Don Ordonio</hi> (this Mans Son) and <hi>Don Alonſo</hi> the Third, <hi>Don Garzia</hi> and <hi>Don Ordonio</hi> the Second; all four Kings by orderly Succeſſion: It hapned that in the year of <hi>Christ</hi> 924, <hi>Don Ordonio</hi> the Second dying, left four Sons and one Daughter lawfully begotten, and yet the State of <hi>Spain</hi> diſplaced them all, and gave the Kingdom to their Uncle <hi>Don Fruela,</hi> ſecond Brother to their Father; and for no other Reaſon, but their being young, and not ſo able to govern as their Uncle was. But after a year this <hi>Fruela</hi> died, leaving many Sons of a full Age; yet the <hi>Spaniards</hi> put them all by the Crown, and thoſe <hi>Don Alonſo</hi> the Fourth.</p>
            <p>And this ſhall ſuffice concerning the Race of <hi>Don Pylao,</hi> firſt Chriſtian King of <hi>Spain,</hi> after the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of the <hi>Moors.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:63101:20"/>
            <p>Now for avoiding prolixity we'll omit many Inſtances that are for our purpoſe, and be content to repeat a few of latter Date. And,</p>
            <p>Firſt, In the year of <hi>Chriſt</hi> 1276. <hi>Don Sancho</hi> (Sirnamed <hi>El Bravo,</hi> for his great Valour) was choſen, and his Nephews, who were Heirs appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, put back, becauſe he weas a great Warriour, and more like to manage better the Matters of War than they: And this was done in a General Parliament, which was held at <hi>Segovia</hi> in the year 1276. and the two Princes his Nephews were put in Priſon; but afterwards by the interceſſion of their Uncle King <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> they were releas'd, and had certain Lands given them; and of them came the Dukes of <hi>Medina Coeli,</hi> and all the reſt of the Houſe of <hi>Cerda,</hi> which are of great Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not long after this,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Garab.</hi> lib. 15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1. An. 1363.</note> when <hi>Don Pedro</hi> (Sirnamed <hi>The Cruel</hi>) King of <hi>Caſtile</hi> was driven out, and his Baſtard-Brother <hi>Henry</hi> the Second ſet up in his place; <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> having Married <hi>Dono Conſtantia,</hi> the ſaid King <hi>Peters</hi> Daughter and Heir pretended by Succeſſion to the ſaid Crown of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> which was really his Right; but yet the State of <hi>Spain</hi> denyed it flatly, and defended it by Arms, and prevailed againſt <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> as did alſo the Race of <hi>Henry</hi> the Baſtard againſt his lawful Brother, and the Race of <hi>Don Sancho</hi> the Uncle againſt his lawful Nephews; and this hapned in the third and principal Deſcent of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Kings, when this Matter of Succeſſion was moſt aſſuredly and perfectly eſtabliſht; and yet who will deny the Kings of <hi>Spain,</hi> who held
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:63101:20"/>under the latter Titles, To be true and lawful Kings?</p>
            <p>By which it appears, how frequently the Line of Succeſſion has been altered in <hi>Spain,</hi> upon any reaſonable Conſideration, which they imagined to be for the Publick good: And the like we ſhall find in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> which we ſhall begin to treat of.</p>
            <p>Now concerning the State of <hi>France,</hi> thô ſince the Entrance of King <hi>Pharamond</hi> with his <hi>Franks</hi> out of <hi>Germany,</hi> which was about the year of <hi>Chriſt</hi> 419. they have never had any Stranger come to wear the Crown, which they attribute to their <hi>Salick</hi> Law, that forbids Womens Reign; yet they have twice chang'd their whole Race and Linage of Kings, once by the Entrance of King <hi>Pepin,</hi> who put out the Line of <hi>Pharamond,</hi> about the year 751. and again in the promotion of <hi>Hugo Capetus,</hi> who put out the Line of <hi>Pepin</hi> in the year 988. ſo as they have had three Deſcents and Races of Kings, as well as the <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I'le paſs over all the firſt Race of the <hi>Franch</hi> Kings, as I alſo did the <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> becauſe ſome men may ſay, That the Commonwealth and Law of Succeſſion was not ſo well ſetled in thoſe days, as it was afterwards in the time of <hi>Pepin, Charles</hi> the Great, and their Deſcendents. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall only mention the ſecond Rank, which began with the Excluſion and Depoſition of their lawful King <hi>Childerick</hi> the Third, and Election of King <hi>Pepin</hi> in the year of <hi>Chriſt</hi> 781, after 22 Kings, which had Reigned of the firſt Line of <hi>Pharamond,</hi> for the ſpace of Three hundred years.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:63101:21"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:63101:21"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:63101:22"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:63101:22"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:63101:23"/>
            <p>This King Reigned 18 years, being a famous King, as all the World knows, left his Kingdom by Succeſſion to his eldeſt Son <hi>Charles,</hi> Sirnamed aſter <hi>The Great,</hi> for his Famous and Heroical Acts. And thô the whole Kingdom belong'd to him by right of Succeſſion, yet did the Realm of <hi>France</hi> ſhew her Authority in his Admiſſion,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rard. du <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilan. <hi>lib 3.</hi>
               </note> as the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian relates in theſe Words; <hi>King</hi> Pepin <hi>being dead, the</hi> French <hi>choſe for their King his two Sons,</hi> Charles <hi>and</hi> Carlomon, <hi>on condition that they ſhould divide the Realm equally betwixt them;</hi> which was a heavy Condition to the elder Brother to part with half his Kingdom.</p>
            <p>After theſe Brothers had Reigned together three years. King <hi>Carlomon</hi> died, and left many Sons; but the Lords Spiritual and Temporal of <hi>France</hi> Swore Allegiance to <hi>Charles,</hi> without any reſpect to the Children of <hi>Carlomon,</hi> who by right of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion ſhould have been preferred.</p>
            <p>After <hi>Charles</hi> the Great Reigned his Son <hi>Lewis</hi> the Firſt, Sirnamed <hi>Debonnaire,</hi> of his Courteſie, who entred with great Applauſe of all Men, for the exceeding grateful Memory of his Father; but he was Depoſed by the means of his Sons, and was put in a Monaſtery; thô after he came to Reign again,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erard.</hi> lib. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. 834.</note> and his fourth Son by his ſecond Wife named <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Bold,</hi> ſucceded him in the Crown, after many Battels againſt his elder Brother <hi>Lothair,</hi> to whom it belong'd by Succeſſion.</p>
            <p>After <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Beld</hi> ſucceeded <hi>Lewis</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, who was the third Son, for the Second died before his Father; and the Eldeſt was put by for his ill Demeanour: This <hi>Lewis</hi> alſo had like to have been deprived by the States at his Entrance,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63101:23"/>for the Hatred conceived againſt his Father,<note place="margin">Gerard. <hi>lib. 1.</hi>
               </note> had he not call'd a Perliament at <hi>Campeigne,</hi> and ſweetned the People and Nobility with many fair Promiſes. This <hi>Lewis</hi> left two Baſtards by a Concubine, who were call'd <hi>Lewis</hi> and <hi>Carlomon,</hi> as alſo an Infant newly born of his lawful Wife <hi>Adeltrude,</hi> Daughter to King <hi>Alfred</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> which Infant was King of <hi>France</hi> after, by the Name of <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Simple,</hi> thô not immediately after the Death of his Fahter: For the Nobles of <hi>France</hi> ſaid. <hi>They had need of a Man to be King, and not a Child;</hi> and ſo the whole State of <hi>France</hi> choſe for their Kings the two afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Baſtards; and they were Crowned moſt ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and divided the whole Realm between them,<note place="margin">An. 881.</note> and Queen <hi>Adeltrude</hi> with her Child (true Heir of <hi>France</hi>) fled into <hi>England</hi> to her Fahter, and there kept him many years; in which time ſhe ſaw four or five Kings Reign in his place ſucceſſively.</p>
            <p>Of theſe two Baſtards, the Elder named <hi>Lewis</hi> Reigned but Four years, and died without Iſſue, the ſecond, named <hi>Carlomon,</hi> lived but one year after him, and left a Son called <hi>Lewis,</hi> which ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded him in the Kingdom by the name of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Fiſth, and Sirnamed <hi>Faineant,</hi> for his idle and ſlothful Life; for which, as alſo for his vicious Behaviour, and in particular for taking out and Marrying a Nun of the Abby of S. <hi>Saveour,</hi> he was depriv'd and made a Monk in the Abby of S. <hi>Denis,</hi> where he died, and in his place was choſen King of <hi>France,</hi> and Crown'd with great Solemnity, <hi>Charles</hi> the Fourth, Emperour of <hi>Rome,</hi> who was Nephew to <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Bold,</hi> before mentioned; and therefore the <hi>French.</hi> Hiſtorians ſay, That he came to the Crown, partly by Succeſſion, and partly by
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:63101:24"/>Election; but for Succeſſion we ſee it was of no account, being <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Simple</hi> the right Heir was alive in <hi>England,</hi> and as it were forgotten, being they had thrice excluded him, and would not receive him, after they had deprived <hi>Charles</hi> for his evil Government; and rather choſe one <hi>Odo,</hi> Earl of <hi>Baris</hi> and Duke of <hi>Angiers,</hi> and cauſed him to be Crown'd.</p>
            <p>But after a few years being weary of this Man's Government, and moved with Compaſſion towards the Youth in <hi>England,</hi> they Depoſed him while he was abſent in <hi>Gaſcony,</hi> and call'd <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Simple</hi> out of <hi>England,</hi> and reſtor'd him to the Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> leaving only to <hi>Odo</hi> the State of <hi>Aquitain,</hi> with Title of a Duke, wherewith in rine he contented himſelf, ſeeing he could get no more. But yet his Poſterity by virtue of this Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, ever after pretended a Title to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> and never deſiſted until by <hi>Hugo Capetus</hi> they got it; for <hi>Hugh</hi> was deſcended of this King and Duke <hi>Odo.</hi> This <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Simple</hi> was decoy'd into the Caſtle of <hi>Perene</hi> in <hi>Picardy,</hi> where he was made Priſoner, and fore'd to reſign his Kingdom unto <hi>Ralph</hi> King of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and ſoon after he died in the Caſtle and his Queen <hi>Odin</hi> and Engliſh Woman fled into <hi>England,</hi> with her little Son <hi>Lewis,</hi> unto her Uncle King <hi>Adelſtan,</hi> as Queen <hi>Adeltrude</hi> had done before.</p>
            <p>But this new King <hi>Ralph</hi> lived but three years aſter, and then the States of <hi>France</hi> conſidering the Title of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Lawful Son of <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> which <hi>Lewis</hi> was commonly called by the name of <hi>d'Outremere,</hi> that is, beyond Sea, being he was brought up in <hi>England;</hi> the ſaid States being
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:63101:24"/>continually ſolicited by the Ambaſſadors of King <hi>Adelſtan,</hi> and by <hi>William</hi> Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> in behalf of the young Prince; they reſolved to call him home, as they had done his Father, and to admit and Crown him King, and ſo they did; and he Reigned Twenty ſeven years, and was a good Prince, and died peaceably in his Bed in the year of <hi>Chriſt</hi> 945.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Lewis d'Outremere</hi> left two Sons behind him, the eldeſt ſucceeded him by the name of <hi>Lothair</hi> the Firſt, and the youngeſt he made Duke of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain. Lothair</hi> dying left one Son named <hi>Lewis,</hi> who ſucceeded him by the name of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Fifth; but dying without Iſſue, the Crown was to have gone by Lineal Succeſſion to his Uncle <hi>Charles,</hi> Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> ſecond Son of <hi>Lewis d'Outremere;</hi> but the States of <hi>France</hi> put him byfor miſlike of his Perſon; choſe <hi>Hugo Capetus</hi> Earl of <hi>Paris,</hi> and ſo ended the ſecond Line of <hi>Pepin,</hi> and of <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> and entred the Race of <hi>Capetus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now thô all the French Chronicles are carneſt defenders of their Law of Succeſſion yet they juſtifie the Title of <hi>Capetus</hi> againſt <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain,</hi> as may appear by the Words of an ancient and diligent Chronicler of the Abby of S. <hi>Denis,</hi> who defends King <hi>Capetus</hi> in theſe Words: <hi>We may not grant by any means, that</hi> Hugh Capet <hi>ſhould be eſteemed an Invader or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper of the Crown of</hi> France, <hi>ſeeing the Lords, Prelates and Princes of the Realm did call him to this Dignity, and choſe him for their King and Sovereign Lord.</hi> Upon which Words <hi>Belforeſt</hi> ſaith, as follows:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bel.</hi> lib 3. cap 1.</note> 
               <hi>I have laid beſore you the Words and Cenſure of this good and religious Man, for they ſeem to me to touch the quick;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63101:25"/>for in truth we cannot defend the Title of</hi> Capetus <hi>by any means from <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation and Felony, but by juſtifying his coming to the Crown, by the conſent and good will of the Commonwealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And theſe Inſtances out of the ſecond Line of <hi>France,</hi> I take to be ſufficient proof of our Aſſertion, without going any further; for if we do but number theſe Kings already named of this ſecond Race, from <hi>Pepin</hi> to <hi>Capet</hi> (which are about Seventeen in Two hundred thirty eight years) we ſhall ſind, that not few, but the moſt part of them did both enter and enjoy their Crown and Dignity contrary to the Law of Lineal Deſcent, and of next Succeſſion by Blood.</p>
            <p>We ſhall therefore inſtance ſome Examples for our purpoſe out of the Engliſh Hiſtory, and ſo conclude this Point.</p>
            <p>Firſt then it's to be noted, That the Realm of <hi>England</hi> hath had as great variety, changes and diverſity in the Races of their Kings, as any Nation in the World: For after the <hi>Britains,</hi> it had <hi>Romans</hi> for their Governours for many years, and then of them and their <hi>Roman</hi> Blood, they had Kings of their own, as appears by that Valiant King <hi>Aurelius Ambroſius,</hi> who reſiſted ſo manfully the <hi>Saxons</hi> for a time; after his they had Kings of the <hi>Saxon</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Blood, and after them of the <hi>Danes,</hi> and then of the Normans, and after them again of the <hi>French;</hi> and laſt of all of the <hi>Scotch,</hi> of whom King <hi>james</hi> the Sixth was deſcended, which continues to this day.</p>
            <p>Now I mean to paſs over the firſt and ancient Races of Kings, as well of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> and <hi>Roman,</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:63101:25"/>as alſo of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Races, until King <hi>Egbert</hi> the Firſt of that Name, King of the <hi>Weſt Saxons,</hi> and almoſt of all the reſt of <hi>England</hi> beſides, who therefore is ſaid to be properly the firſt Monarch of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Blood, as he that firſt commanded the Realm to be called <hi>England,</hi> which ever ſince has been obſerv'd.</p>
            <p>Thsi <hi>Egbert</hi> was baniſh'd the Realm by King <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricus,</hi> for the ſuſpected that he might be choſen King, by reaſon of his great Proweſs and Valour. He lived many years in <hi>France</hi> under the Famous King <hi>Pepin;</hi> afterwards hearing <hi>Britrious</hi> was dead, he came into <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Polydor.</hi> lib. 4.</note> and was choſen King by uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Conſent of the People; and he prov'd one of the beſt Kings that ever the <hi>Saxons</hi> had before, or perhaps after; and he and King <hi>Pepin</hi> of <hi>France</hi> began their Reigns as it were together, and came both to their Crown by no other Title, but the Election of the People.</p>
            <p>This King <hi>Egbert</hi> left a lawful ſon behind him named <hi>Ethelwolf,</hi> who ſucceeded him in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and was a Famous a Man as his Fahter. This <hi>Ethelwolf</hi> had four lawful ſons, who all in their turns ſucceeded by juſt and lawful Order in the Crown, <hi>viz. Ethelbald, Ethelbert, Ethelred</hi> and <hi>Alfred,</hi> and all the latter Three were moſt excellent Princes, eſpecially <hi>Alfred,</hi> who drow <hi>Rollo,</hi> that Famous Captain of the <hi>Danes</hi> from the Borders of <hi>England</hi> with all his Company into <hi>France,</hi> where he got the Country, then name <hi>Neuſtria,</hi> and now <hi>Normandy,</hi> and was the firſt Duke of that Nation, from whom our <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour came after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in the 6th Deſcent.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:63101:26"/>
            <p>This <hi>Alfred</hi> left one Son behind him named <hi>Edward,</hi> who dying left two Sons, lawfully begotten of his Wife <hi>Edigna,</hi> one called <hi>Edmond,</hi> the other <hi>Eldred,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Polydor.</hi> lib. 5. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tow</hi> pag. 130.</note> and a third Illegitimate, nam'd <hi>Adelſtan,</hi> whom he had by a Concubine. This laſt was preferr'd to the Crown before the other two legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate princes, only for his Valour and Conduct.</p>
            <p>This Man dying without Iſſue, his lawful Brother <hi>Edmond,</hi> put back before, was admitted to the Crown, who Reigned ſix years, and left two lawful Sons; but they bing young were both put back, and their Uncle <hi>Eldred</hi> preferr'd before them; who after Nine years Reign died without Iſſue, and ſo his elder Nephew <hi>Edwin</hi> was admitted to the Crown, who after four years was Depos'd for his lew'd and vitious Life and his younger Brother <hi>Edgar</hi> admitted in his place.</p>
            <p>This King <hi>Edgar,</hi> who entred by Depoſitio; of his Brother, was one of the rareſt Princes that the World had in his time, both for peace and War, Juſtice, Piety and Valour. He leſt two Sons by different Wives, <hi>Edmond</hi> and <hi>Etheldred;</hi> the firſt was Murther'd, after which many good Men of the Realm were of Opinion, not to admit the Succeſſion of <hi>Etheldred,</hi> both in reſpect of the Murther of King <hi>Edward</hi> his elder Brother, committed for his ſake; as alſo for that he ſeem'd a Man very unſit for Government; and of this Opinion was that holy Man <hi>Dunſtand,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who in flat words denied to Conſecrate him; but ſeeing the moſt part of the Realm incline to his ſide, he told that it would repent them afterwards, and that in his Life the Nation ſhould be deſtroy'd; as indeed it was, and he forc'd to <hi>Normandy,</hi> and left <hi>Sweno</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:63101:26"/>and his <hi>Danes</hi> in the poſſeſſion of the Realm, thô after <hi>Sweno</hi>'s Death he return'd and died in <hi>London.</hi> He had two Wives, the firſt an Engliſh Woman, by whom he had prince <hi>Edmond,</hi> Sirnam'd <hi>Ironſide,</hi> for his great ſtrength and courage.</p>
            <p>Now he that will conſider the paſſage of the Crown of <hi>England</hi> from the death of <hi>Edmond Iron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide,</hi> eldeſt Son of King <hi>Etheldred,</hi> until the acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition thereof by <hi>William</hi> Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> will eaſily ſe what Authority the Commonwealth hath had, to alter Titles of Succeſſion, according as pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick neceſſity required.</p>
            <p>Now ſince King <hi>William</hi> the Firſt, commonly call'd the Conquerour, (thô in truth he never grounded his Title upon any thing, but the Election of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor and Conſent of the people) the excluſion of Princes againſt the ordinary courſe of Succeſſion, is more notorious than in elder times; therefore I ſhall only refer the Reader to their particular Lives, who ſucceeded before the lawful Heirs by propinquity of Blood. As firſt, <hi>William Rufus</hi> and <hi>henry</hi> the Firſt, before <hi>Robert</hi> their elder Brother, King <hi>Stephen</hi> before <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, and King <hi>John</hi> before <hi>Arthur</hi> Duke of <hi>Britain.</hi> Some years afte, when the Barons and States of <hi>England</hi> diſlik'd the Governent of King <hi>John,</hi> they rejected him and choſe <hi>Lewis</hi> the Prince of <hi>France</hi> to be their King, and ſwore Fealty to him at <hi>London,</hi> and depriv'd the young Prince <hi>Henry</hi> his Son; but after the death of his Father king <hi>John,</hi> they recall'd again that Sentence, and admitted this <hi>Henry</hi> to the Crown by the name of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and diſannull'd the oath, and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance made to <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> Now from this <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, the Houſes of <hi>Britany, Lancaſter</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:63101:27"/>and <hi>York,</hi> do ſeem to iſſue, as a triple Branch our of one Tree.</p>
            <p>Now if we conſider the Titles of the Kings of the Houſe of <hi>York</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> we ſhall ſee plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the beſt of all their Titles (after the depoſition of King <hi>Richard</hi> the Second) depended moſt or the Authority of the Commonwealth; for as the People were affected, and the greater part prevailed, ſo were their Titles either confirm'd, altered, or diſannulled by Parliament; and yet we may ſafely affirm, that either part, when they were in poſſeſſion of the Crown, and confirm'd therein by parliament, were true and lawful Kings, and that God concur'd with them, as with true Princes for government of their People: For if we ſhould deny this Point, great Inconveniences would follow, and we ſhould ſhake the States of moſt princes in the World at this day, as by Examples which I have already alledg'd may appear. And ſO I ſhall end this point, affirming, That as propinquity of Blood is a great preheminence towards the attaining of any Crown, yet it doth not bind the Commonwealth to admit it, if weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier Reaſons ſhould urge the contrary.</p>
            <p>Now it will be a further proof of what I have before alledg'd, (<hi>viz.</hi> That all Commonwealths have prefix laws to their Princes, which they are as much bound to keep as any Subject) if we conſider their oaths at their Admiſſion or Coronation. And firſt of the Emperour, who Swears to defend the Chriſtian Religion, to miniſter Juſtice equally to all Men, to keep and obſerve all laws and priviledges of the Empire; not to alienate or engage the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Empire, to condemn no man but by courſe of Law, and that whatſoever he does otherwiſe,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:63101:27"/>ſhall be void and of no validity. Unto theſe Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles he Swears firſt by his Legates, and he gives a Copy of his oath to each Elector, and after he goes to be Crown'd; where in the middle of Maſt the Archbiſhop of <hi>Colen</hi> asks in the preſence of all the the People, Whether he is ready to Swear to the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Articles? and he anſwers that he is; then the Archbiſhop leads him to the high Altar, where he Swears to them in expreſs words; which being done, the Archbiſhop turning to the princes of the Empire and People there preſent, asks them Whether they be content to ſwear Obedience and Fealty to him? who anſwers, Yes: then he's Anointed, and the other two Archbiſhop lead him into the <hi>Veſtry,</hi> where Deacons are ready to put on his Robes; then the Biſhop of <hi>Colen</hi> delivereth him a drawn Sword, and puts a Ring on his Finger, and a Scepter in his Hand; and then the three Archbiſhops put the Crown on his head, and ſo he's plac'd on the Imperial Throne, where all the Princes ſwear Obedience to him.</p>
            <p>Now it's to be noted, that the Emperour Swears three times, twice himſelf, and once by his Deputies, before his Subjects Swear once to him.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Polonia,</hi> the manner of Crowning thieir King is in ſubſtance the ſame as of the Emperour. His Oath is in theſe Words; <hi>I do promiſe and ſwear before God and his Angels, that I will do Law and Juſtice to all, and keep the Peace of Chriſt's Church, and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of his Catholick Faith; and if (which God forbid) I ſhould break my Oath, I am content that the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of this Kingdom, owe no Duty or Obedience unto me, as God ſhall help me, and gods Holy Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>Spain</hi> I find, that the manner of admitting their Kings was different, and not the ſame before and after
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:63101:28"/>the deſtruction thereof by the <hi>Moors;</hi> but yet in both times their Kings did Swear in effect the ſelf-ſame Points, which before have been mentioned in other Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Ambroſio Moral.</hi> reports,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ambro. Moral.</hi> lib. 13. cap. 2.</note> That a certain law was found writen in the <hi>Gothiſh</hi> Tongue, and left ſince the time of <hi>Don Pelayo</hi> the firſt King after the <hi>Moors;</hi> which preſcrib'd, how Men muſt make their King in <hi>Spain,</hi> and how he muſt ſwear to the priviledges and Liberties of that nation. Before all things it's eſtabliſht for a law, Liberty and Priviledge of <hi>Spain,</hi> that the Kings ſhall be made by Voices and Conſent perpetually; to the intent, that no Evil king may enter without the Conſent of the people, ſeeing they are to give him that which with their Blood and Labours they have gain'd from the <hi>Moors.</hi> Thus far goes the firſt Article of this Law, which is the more to be noted, becauſe the moſt ancient of the Spaniſh Hiſtorians do ſay, that from this <hi>Don Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layo</hi> the Succeſſion of their Kings was ever by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinquity of Blood; and yet we ſee, that Election was joyned with it in expreſs terms. The ſecond part of that Law contain'd the Ceremonies us'd in thoſe old times at the admiſſion of their Kings.</p>
            <p>Now as fro <hi>France,</hi> their ancient Ceremonies of Crowning their old Kings, was much after the manner which I noted before out of the Law of <hi>Don Pelayo,</hi> firſt King of <hi>Spain</hi> after the <hi>Moors:</hi> But as concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the principal Point of that Action, which is the ſubſtance of admitting the King unto his Royal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and of Oath by him made of governing well and juſtly, and of the reciprocal Oath of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience made to him by his Subjects, it was not much different from what is now uſed: The Archbiſhop
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:63101:28"/>of <hi>Rhemes</hi> being veſted in Pontifical Attire, and come to the Altar to ſay Maſt 9where the King is alſo upon a high Seat placed) he turns to him and ſays theſe ſords; <hi>Sir, that which we require at your hands this day is, that you promiſe unto us, that you'l keep all Canonical priviledges, Law and Juſtice, due to be kept and defended, as a good King is bound to do in his realm.</hi> To which the King anſwers, <hi>I do promiſe to every one of you, that I will keep and maintain all Canonical priviledges, Law and Juſtice due to every Man, to the utmoſt of my power, and by Gods help will defend you, as a good King is bound to do.</hi> This being done, the king Swears and makes his oath, laying his hands upon the goſpel, in theſe Words following; <hi>I do ſwear and promiſe to all Chriſtian People, ſubject unto me, theſe Points enſuing: Firſt, To procure that all my Subjects be kept in union of the Church, and I will defend them from all Exceſs, Rapin, Extortion and Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. Secondly, I will take care that in all Judgments, Juſtice ſhall be kept, with Equity and Mercy. Thirdly, I'le endeavour (as much as poſſible) to chaſe and drive out of my Realm, all ſuch as the Curch hath, or ſhall declare Hereticks, as God ſhall help me, and his holy Goſpel.</hi> Thus Sweareth the King, and then kiſſes the Book, and immediately is ſung <hi>Te Deum;</hi> and then the King's veſted, and the Ring, Scepter, Crown, and the other Kingly Ornaments are put on him, with Declaration firſt what they ſignifie; and then particular Prayers are made to God, that their ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſication may be by the King fulfilled.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>England</hi> hath particularly taken her Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies from <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Belfor. <hi>in vita</hi> Phil. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> being many of our Engliſh Kings have come from thence, as <hi>William</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror, born in <hi>Normandy, Stephen</hi> Earl of <hi>Blois</hi> and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:63101:29"/>
               <hi>Bullen,</hi> a French-man, and <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, born likewiſe in <hi>France,</hi> and Son to the Earl of <hi>Anjou.</hi> Now the Arcbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> doth ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily perform the Ceremonies at the Coronation in <hi>England,</hi> as the Archbiſhop of <hi>Rhemes</hi> doth in <hi>France;</hi> and we may collect the ſubſtance of what the Kings of <hi>England</hi> formerly ſwore, from the Biſhops Letter to <hi>Henry</hi> the Seocnd, as alſo from the Speech of <hi>Thomas Arundel,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> to <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth. In the former are theſe Words; <hi>Do you remember the Confeſſion which you made and laid upon the Altar at</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>for keeping and defending the liberty of the Church when you were Conſecrated and Anointed King by</hi> Theobaldus <hi>our predeceſſor?</hi> By which it appears. that he not only Swears, but gave up his oath alſo in Writing; and for more ſolemnity and obligation, laid it down with his own hands upon the Altar.</p>
            <p>That to <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, was occaſioned by his attempting to take the temporalties from the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy; wherefore the Archbiſhop deſired him to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Oath which he made, that he would delend the Church and Miniſters thereof; and therefore pray'd him, to permit and ſuffer the Church to enjoy the Priviledges and Liberties which it did in the time of his Predeceſſors; and he alſo deſired him, to conſider his Promiſe made to the Realm, which was, <hi>That he would preferve unto every Man their Right and Title, ſo far as in him lay.</hi> At which the King was ſo moved, as he would hear no more of that Bill of Laity; but ſaid, <hi>He would leave the Church in as good, or better condition than he feaund it.</hi> The other conditions of good Government are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſet down in the king of <hi>Englands</hi> oath, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:63101:29"/>by ancient Writers in theſe Words;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Holing.</hi> p. 47 &amp; 1005.</note> 
               <hi>That he will (during his Life) bear due reverence unto Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, and to his Church; and that he will admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter Law and Juſtice equally to them all, and take away all unjuſt Laws.</hi> Which after he had ſworn, then did the Archbiſhop 9turning to the people) declare whatthe King has promiſed, and by an Herald at Arms asked their Conſents, Whether they were content to ſubmit themſelves unto this Man, as unto their King, or no, under the Conditions propoſed? And when they have yielded, the Archbiſhop beings to put on the Regal Ornaments, as the <hi>Sword, Ring, Scepter</hi> and <hi>Crown,</hi> as in the French Coronation, and bids him hold his Place and keep his Oath.</p>
            <p>And this is the ſum of the Engliſh Coronation, which may be read in <hi>Stow;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stow</hi> in the Life of <hi>Ric.</hi> 2.</note> but eſpecially the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions as well of the ſaid <hi>henry</hi> the Fourth laſt mentioned; as alſo of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth, at their firſt Entrances to the Crown; for in the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of KIng <hi>Henry, Stow</hi> ſhews how the People were demanded thrice. Whether they would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to take him for their King? And then the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop read to them, what this new King was bound by oath unto. At the Admiſſion alſo of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth, <hi>Staw</hi> ſhews how the Peoples Conſent was ſolemnly demanded in <hi>S. Johns</hi> Fields by <hi>London;</hi> notwithſtanding King <hi>Edward</hi> had prov'd his title by Succeſſion in the parliament at <hi>Weſlminſter; And now the Conſent of the people being had,</hi> (or, <hi>He being thus Elected,</hi> as <hi>Stow</hi>'s Words are) <hi>he was with great Royalty convey'd to</hi> Weſtminſter,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stow</hi> in the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. p. 7</note> 
               <hi>and in the Hall ſet in the Kings Seat, with</hi> S. Edwards <hi>Scepter in his hand; and then the people were askt if they would have him King? and they cried,</hi> Yea, yea. Thus far <hi>Stow.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:63101:30"/>
            <p>Now if any except againſt theſe Inſtances, becauſe they entred and began their Reigns upon the depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of other Kings then living, let them look into the Coronations of <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>6th,</hi> Queen <hi>mary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and they will find, That the Conſent of the People and their Acceptation of thoſe Princes, is not only demanded by the publick Cry of a He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rald at Arms, which ſtands on the ſide of the Scaffold whereon the Prince is Crowned, and the peoples Anſwer expected till they cry, <hi>Yes, yes;</hi> but alſo that the ſaid Princes gave their Corporal Oath unto the Biſhiop who Crowned them, to uphold and manintain the true Faith, with the Liberties and Priviledges of the Church; as alſo to govern by Juſtice and Law: Which Oath no doubt hath been moſt ſolemnly ſworn by all the Kings and Queens of <hi>England,</hi> from the days of <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor at the leaſt, and whoſoever would ſee more Points of theſe Oaths ſet down in particular, let him read <hi>Magna Charta</hi> and he'l be ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>By all which, and by much more that might be alledg's in this matter, it is evident, that this Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Bargain and Contract between the King and his Common wealth at his firſt Admiſſion, is as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and firm (notwithſtanding any pretence or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt he hath by Succeſſion) as any Contract or Marriage in the World can be; which is an act that lively expreſſeth the other; ſo as we muſt condemn the Aſſertions of thoſe Men, as abſurd, baſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious, who ſay, That only Succeſſion of Bloor is the thing without further Approbation, which makes a King, and that the Peoples Conſent to him who is next by Birth, is nothing at all needful, be he what he will; and that his Admiſſion or Coronation
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:63101:30"/>is only a matter of external Ceremony, without any effect, for increaſe or confirmation of his Right.</p>
            <p>having now proved by Examples of our own and neighbouring Nations, That all their Kings have been Sworn to the obſervation of their Laws and Conſtitutions, before their Coronation or Admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance by the Commonwealth; I ſhall proceed to make it appear, That Kings in all Chriſtian King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms have been Depoſed for breach of the aforeſaid Original Contract; but with this Proteſtation before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, that I do not intend any diſreſpect againſt the Sacred Authority of Princes and Governours, but only to ſhew, that as nothing under God is more honourable, proſitable or Sovereign, than a good prince; ſo nothing is more peſtilent, or bringeth ſo great deſtruction and deſolation, as an evil one. And therefore as the whole Body is of more Authority than the Head, and may cure it, if diſcompoſed if they infeſt the reſt; ſeeing that a Body Civil may have many heads by Succeſſion, and is not always bound to one as a Body Natural is; which Body Natural, if it had the ſame ability, that when it hath an aking or ſickly Head, it could cut if off and take another; I doubt not but it would do ſo, and that all Men would confeſs that it had ſufficient Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Reaſon to do the ſame, rather than all the other Parts ſhould periſh, or live in pain and continual torment. But yet the matter is much clearer that we have in hand for eaſing our ſelves of wicked Princes, as I ſhall now begin to declare.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore, I ſhould alledge ſome Examples out of Scripture, but that ſome Men may chance to object, <hi>That thoſe things recorded there of the</hi> Jews, <hi>are not ſo much to be reputed for acts of the Commonwealth, as
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:63101:31"/>for particular Ordinations of God himſelf:</hi> Which yet is not any thing againſt me, but rather makes much for our purpoſe, by reaſon the matter is much more authorized hereby, ſeeing whatſoever God did ordain and exerciſe in his Commonwealth, may alſo be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis'd by others, having Gods Authority and Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation for it. Wherefore I ſhall haſten to Examples nearer home, and more proper to the particular pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe we treat of; yet I cannot omit noting two or three out of the Bible, that do appertain to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe alſo; and theſe are the deprivations of two wicked Kings of <hi>Judah, Saul</hi> and <hi>Amon;</hi> (thô both were lawfully placed in that Dignity) and the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Joſias</hi> in their rooms, who were the two moſt excellent Princes that ever that Nation, or any other ever had to govern them.</p>
            <p>And firſt, King <hi>Saul,</hi> thô he was choſen by God to that Royal Throne, yet he was ſlain by the <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> by Gods Order, as it was foretold him, for his diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and not fulfilling the Law, and living within the Limits preſcribed unto him. <hi>Amon</hi> was lawful King alſo, and that by Natural deſcent and ſucceſſion; for he was Son and Heir to King <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> whom he ſucceeded; and yet he was ſlain by his own People, becauſe he walked not in the way preſcribed unto him by God: And unto theſe two Kings ſo deprived God gave two Succeſſors, the like whereof are not to be found in the whole Race of Kings for a thouſand years together; for of <hi>Joſias</hi> it is written, <hi>He did that which was right in the ſight of god, neither did he decline to the right hand nor to the left;</hi> He reigned 32 years; and <hi>Jeremiah</hi> the Prophet, who lived in his time, loved this good King ſo extremely, as he never ceaſed to lament his Death. As for King <hi>David,</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:63101:31"/>it will be needleſs to report how excellent a King he was; for (as many Learned men do note) he was a moſt perfect Pattern for all Kings that ſhould follow in the World; not only in matters of Religion Piety and Devotion, but alſo of Chivalry Valour, Wiſdom and Policy; neither is it true which <hi>Machiavel,</hi> and ſome others of his School affirm, for defacing of Chriſtian Vertue, That Religion and Piety are often Lets to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick and wiſe government, and do weaken the high Spirits of magnanimous Men, to take in hand great Enterprizes for the Commonwealth. This (I ſay) is extremely falſe, for Grace doth not deſtroy or corrupt, but perfecteth Nature; ſo as he who by Nature is valiant, wife, liberal or politick, ſhall be more, if he's alſo pious and religious. Which is evident in King <hi>David,</hi> who notwithſtanding all his Piety, omitted nothing belonging to the State and Government of a noble, wife and politick Prince.</p>
            <p>And now if we leave the Hebrews and come to the Romans, we ſhall find many notable things in that State for our purpoſe: For when <hi>Romulus</hi> their firſt King declin'd into Tyranny, he was put by by the Senate, and in his place was choſen <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> (a notable Prince) who preſcrib'd all their order of Religion and manner of Sacrifices, imitating therein the Rites and Ceremonies of the <hi>Jews,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> and other Fathers do note; he began alſo the building of their <hi>Capitol,</hi> and did other beneficial things for that Commonwealth. Again, when <hi>Tarquinus</hi> the Proud, their <hi>7th</hi> and laſt King was expell'd for his evil Government, we ſee the ſucceſs was proſperous, for that not only no hurt came thereby to the State, but exceeding benefit, being their Government and increaſe of Empire was ſo proſperous under their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:63101:32"/>that whereas at the end of their Kingly Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they had but 15 Miles Territory without their City, it is well known, that when the Conſuls Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ended, and was changed by <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> their Territory reached more than 15000 Miles in compaſs; being they had not only <hi>Europe</hi> under their Dominion, but the principal parts of <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Africa</hi> alſo; ſo as this Chaſtiſement ſo juſtly inflicted on <hi>Tarquin,</hi> was profitable and beneficial to their Commonwealth alſo. Moreover, when <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> had broken all Law both human and divine, and taken all Government into his own hands, he was (as the World knows) ſlain by his Senators in the Senate-Houſe, and <hi>Octavianus Auguſtus</hi> prefer'd in his room, who proved the moſt famous Emperour that ever was. When <hi>Nero</hi> the <hi>6th,</hi> Emperour of <hi>Rome,</hi> who ſucceeded lawfully his Uncle <hi>Claudius</hi> in the Empire, was depos'd and ſentenc'd to death by the Senate for his wicked Government, thô Peace en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu'd not preſently; but that <hi>Galba, Otho</hi> and <hi>Vitel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> three Captains of the Empire, made ſome little interludes of Tragical killing one another; yet within few Months the whole Empire by that means fell into <hi>Veſpaſtan</hi> and his Son <hi>Titus</hi>'s hand, two of the beſt Governours that ever thoſe times ſaw.</p>
            <p>The like may be noted of the Noble rank of five excellent Princes, <hi>viz. Nerva, Trajan, Adrian, Antorinus Pius,</hi> and <hi>Marcus Aurelius,</hi> who ſucceeded in the Empire by the juſt Death of cruel <hi>Domitian;</hi> which Execution its thought the Senate ſecretly procured, (not being able to perform it openly by Juſtice) which appears, becauſe when the act was done, the Senate did preſently by publick Decree allow it, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annull'd all his barbarous acts for their exceeding
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:63101:32"/>Cruelty, and commanded his Arms and Memorials to be taken down every where, and choſe for his Succeſſor one <hi>Cocceius Nerva</hi> an <hi>Italian,</hi> a Man of excellent Vertue, by whom they not only enjoy'd the moſt proſperous time of his Government; but of all the four who enſued him, no leſs worthy than himſelf. Not long after the Succeſſion of theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Emperours, there came to the Crown by law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful deſcent, a youth named <hi>Antoninus Heliogabalus,</hi> Son of the Emperour <hi>Antoninus Caracalla,</hi> and Grandchild (as was ſuppoſed) to the famous and noble Emperour <hi>Septimius Severus,</hi> who died in <hi>England;</hi> which Youth, as he was highly honour'd for a time upon the account of his worthy Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father; ſo after for his own Beaſtly life, he was depriv'd and put to death by the Souldiers, at the requeſt and common deſire both of the Senate and People; who ordained alſo in his deteſtation, That no Emperour after him ſhould be call'd <hi>Antonius.</hi> This Man being depoſed as aforeſaid, there was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to the Empire in his room a hopeful young Man of his next Kingdred, named <hi>Alexander Severus,</hi> being admitted by common Conſent both of Senate and People, who prov'd one of the rareſt Princes (for Valour and Vertue) that ever the Roman Empire had; ſo as the excellency of <hi>Severus</hi> ſeemed fully to recompence the wickedneſs of <hi>Heliogabalus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I may name many other ſuch Examples, and among the reſt that of <hi>Maxentius,</hi> who being lawfully poſſeſs'd of the Empire (being Son to <hi>Maximinianus</hi> the Emperour, which Reign'd with <hi>Diocleſian</hi>) yet for his Tyrannical Government that was intolerable, its ſuppoſed that the Senate (not being able to match him in open ſtrength) ſent privily into <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:63101:33"/>to invite <hi>Conſtantine</hi> to come to their relief, and ſo he did; and <hi>Maxentius</hi> being drown'd in the River <hi>Tyber, Conſtantine</hi> (afterwards Sirnam'd the <hi>Great</hi>) ſucceeded in the Empire, who was the Emperour (as the World knows) who firſt publickly profeſſed himſelf a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and planted our Faith over all the World. And ſo I ſhall end with the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire.</p>
            <p>Now if we come lower down, and nearer home, we have yet another Example more remarkable than the reſt; which is, the change of the Empire from the Eaſt to the Weſt, for the evil Government of <hi>Irene</hi> and her Son <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the <hi>6th,</hi> who was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed firſt, and his Eyes put out by his own Mother <hi>Irene,</hi> and the Empire uſurp'd by her; who not being able to Rule it in ſuch order as was requiſite for ſo great a Monarchy, ſhe was deprived thereof by the Sentence of Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the Third, and by Conſent of all the People and Senate of <hi>Rome, Charles</hi> King of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany</hi> (after Sirnamed the <hi>Great</hi>) was Crown'd Emperour of the Weſt; which Succeſſion continues as it were to this day, and many Worthy men have ſucceeded therein, and inſinite acts of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction have been exerciſed by that Authority, which were all unjuſt and Tyrannical, if this change of the Empire, and depoſition of <hi>Irene</hi> and her Son, for their evil Government, had not been lawful. It were too long to run over all other Kingdoms, and therefore I ſhall only touch ſome in thoſe Points that are moſt notorious.</p>
            <p>Now the two famous Changes that have been made in the Royal Line of <hi>France;</hi> the firſt from the Race of <hi>Pharamond</hi> and <hi>Clodoveus</hi> to the Line of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pin,</hi> and the ſecond from the Race of <hi>Pepin</hi> to <hi>Hugo Capetus;</hi> whereon are they founded, but upon the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:63101:33"/>Judicial chaſtiſement and depoſition of two evil Princes, the firſt of <hi>Childeric</hi> the third lawful King of <hi>France,</hi> the ſecond of <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorain,</hi> who was kept Priſoner during his life in the Caſtle of <hi>Orleance?</hi> And thus muhc all the French Hiſtories do affirm, and do attribute to theſe Changes the proſperity and greatneſs of their Kingdom. And ſo much for <hi>France,</hi> where many other Examples might be alledg'd, as of King <hi>Lewis</hi> the Third, Sirnamed <hi>Fainant,</hi> and of <hi>Charles</hi> Sirnamed <hi>Le Groſs.</hi> who ſucceeded him, both of them depos'd by the States of <hi>France,</hi> as before I have noted.</p>
            <p>But now if we ſtep over the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Mountains, and look into <hi>Spain,</hi> where we ſhall not fail of many Examples to our purpoſe, both before the oppreſſion of that Realm by the <hi>Moors,</hi> and after. for before, in the year of Chriſt 630, we read of a lawful King named <hi>Flaveo Suintila,</hi> put down and deprived with his whole Poſterity, in the fourth Council National of <hi>Toledo,</hi> and one <hi>Siſſinando</hi> confirmed in his place;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ambroſio Mora</hi> lib. 11. cap. 19.</note> notwithſtanding that <hi>Suintila</hi> was at the beginning of his Reign, a very good King, and much commended by S. <hi>Iſidorus</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Sevil;</hi> who yet in the ſaid Council was the firſt Man who ſubſcrib'd to his deprivation. After the entrance of the <hi>Moors</hi> alſo, when <hi>Spain</hi> was reduc'd again to order and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Kings;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Garib.</hi> lib. 13 cap. 15.</note> we read that about the year of Chriſt 1282. one <hi>Don Alonſo</hi> the <hi>11th</hi> of that name, King of <hi>Caſtile</hi> and <hi>Leon,</hi> ſucceeded his Father <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> Sirnam'd the <hi>Saint,</hi> and he obtain'd the name of <hi>Sabio</hi> and <hi>Aſtrologio,</hi> that is, of <hi>Wiſe</hi> and ſo an <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> for excelent Learning and peculiar skill in that Art as may appear by the Aſtronomy Tables that at this day go under his Name, which are the moſt perfect and exact that ever were ſet forth, by Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:63101:34"/>of the Learned. This Man, for his evil govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and eſpecially for Tyranny uſed towards two Nephews of his, was depoſed of his Kingdom by a publick Act of Parliament in the Town of <hi>Validolid,</hi> after he had Reigned 30 years; and his Son <hi>Don Sancho</hi> the <hi>4th</hi> was Crown'd in his place, who for his valiant Acts was Sirnam'd <hi>El Bravo,</hi> and it turn'd to the great commodity of the Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>The ſame Country of <hi>Spain</hi> ſome years after, about the year of <hi>Chriſt</hi> 1368,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Garib.</hi> lib. 14. cap. 40, &amp; 41.</note> having to their King one <hi>Don Pedro,</hi> Sirnamed the <hi>Cruel,</hi> who for his inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Proceedings with his Subjects, they depoſed, and ſent for his Baſtard Brother out of <hi>France,</hi> and made him King. And thô <hi>Edward,</hi> Sirnamed the <hi>Black Prince,</hi> by order of his Father <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>3d</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> reſtored the ſaid <hi>Peter</hi> again; yet it was not durable, for that <hi>Henry</hi> having the favour of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> return'd and depriv'd <hi>Peter</hi> the ſecond time, and ſlew him in fight hand to hand, who proved an excellent Prince, and for his great nobility in Converſation, and proweſs in Chivalry, was called <hi>El Cavalero,</hi> the <hi>Knightly King,</hi> and for his exceeding benignity and liberality was Sirnam'd alſo <hi>El delas Mercedes, i.e.</hi> the <hi>King who gave many Gifts,</hi> or the <hi>liberal, frank,</hi> and <hi>bountiful King;</hi> which was a great alteration from King <hi>Peter</hi> the <hi>Cruel,</hi> his Predeceſſor.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Portugal</hi> alſo, before I go out of <hi>Spain,</hi> I will alledge one Example more, which is of <hi>Don Sancho</hi> the <hi>2d,</hi> fourth King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> lawful Son to <hi>Don Alenſo</hi> Sirnam'd <hi>El Gardo, 3d</hi> King of <hi>Portugal.</hi> This <hi>Don Sancho</hi> (after he had Reigned 34 years) was deprived for his defects in Government, by the univerſal Conſent of all <hi>Portugal;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Garib.</hi> lib. 4. de hiſt. <hi>Port.</hi> cap. 19.</note> and this approved by a general Council in <hi>Lions;</hi> and <hi>Don Alonſo,</hi> third Brother to the ſaid
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:63101:34"/>
               <hi>Don Sancho,</hi> ſucceeded; who enjoy'd the Kingdom of <hi>Portugal</hi> proſperouſly and peaceably all the days of his life, and he was a notable King; who among other great Exploits ſet <hi>Portugal</hi> free from all ſubjection,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Garib.</hi> hiſt. <hi>Port.</hi> lib. 34. cap. 20.</note> dependance and homage to the Kingdom of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> which unto his time it had acknowledged, and he left for his Succeſſor his Son and Heir, <hi>Don Dionyſio el Fabricador,</hi> that is, the <hi>Great Builder,</hi> for he built and founded above 44 great Towns in <hi>Portgual,</hi> and was a very excellent Prince.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Polonia, Henry</hi> the <hi>3d,</hi> who was King of <hi>France,</hi> thô before Sworn King of <hi>Poland,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vide <hi>Gagnen.</hi> part. 1.</note> of which Crown he was deprived by publick Act of Parliament, for departing thence without Licence, and not returning at his day, by the State appointed and denounced, by publick Letters of peremptory Commandment. This was a clear Abdication, and the ſaid State pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded againſt him much after the ſame manner, as ours did againſt the late King <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>Denmark, Ciſternus</hi> their lawful King, if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect his deſcent in Blood, being Son to King <hi>John,</hi> who Reigned before him, and Crown'd in his Fathers life, was depoſed for his intolerable Cruelty, and driven into Baniſhment, together with his Wife and three Children, which were all diſinherited and his Uncle <hi>Frederick,</hi> Prince of <hi>Holſatia</hi> was choſen King; and <hi>Ciſternus,</hi> thô he married the Siſter of <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>5th</hi> Emperour of <hi>Germany,</hi> and was Related alſo to <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>8th</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> yet he could never prevail to be reſtored, but paſt his time miſerably, partly in Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and partly in Priſon, till he died.</p>
            <p>Now I think it convenient to end this ſhort Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration with an Example or two out of <hi>England</hi> being I have not read of more remarkable Accidents con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:63101:35"/>this Point, than in the Hiſtory of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: But for brevities ſake, I ſhall content my ſelf with three or four Examples which hapned ſince the Conqueſt, thô I may well look higher, as appears by the deprivation of King <hi>Edwin</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>Now I might inſtance King <hi>John,</hi> who the States had deprived, firſt at <hi>Canterbury</hi> and after at <hi>London,</hi> in the <hi>18th</hi> year of his Reign; but being he was in actual War with the Barons, and had a conſiderable Party to eſpouſe his Quarrel, and not being deprived by Parliament I ſhall therefore paſs it by, not account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſo compleat a Depoſition, as that of <hi>Edward</hi> the Seconds was,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Polydor.</hi> lib. 18.</note> it being done by Act of Parliament aſſembled in <hi>London</hi> in the year 1326, and his Body adjudg'd to perpetual Impriſonment, he being Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner at that time in the Caſtle of <hi>Wallingford,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stow</hi> in the Life of <hi>Edw.</hi> the 2d.</note> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther divers (both Biſhops, Lords and Commoners) were ſent to him, to denounce the Sentence of the Realm againſt him, <hi>viz.</hi> how they had deprived him, and choſen <hi>Edward</hi> his Son in his ſtead: For which act of chaſing his Son he thank'd them heartily, and with many Tears acknowledg'd his own unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Whereupon he was degraded; his name of <hi>King</hi> firſt taken from him, and he appointed to be call'd <hi>Edward</hi> of <hi>Carnarvan;</hi> and then his <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Ring</hi> were taken away, and the Steward of his Houſe brake the Staff of his Office in his preſence, and diſcharged his Servants of their Services, and all other People were diſcharged of their Obedience and Allegiance to him; and towards his Maintenance he had only 100 Marks a year allowed for his Expences, and then he was delivered into the hands of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Keepers, who led him Priſoner from thence to many other places, uſing him with extreme Indignity
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:63101:35"/>in the way, until at laſt they took away his Life in <hi>Berkley</hi> Caſtle, and his Son <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>2d</hi> Reign'd in his ſtead; who (if we reſpect either Valour, Proweſs, length of Reign, acts of Chivalry, or the multitude of Famous Princes his Children left behind him) was one of the nobleſt Kings that ever <hi>England</hi> had.</p>
            <p>After him ſucceeded <hi>Richard</hi> the <hi>2d,</hi> Son and Heir to the renowned Black Prince of <hi>Wales;</hi> who forgetting the miſerable end of his Great Grandfather for evil Government, and the felicity of his Grandfather for the contrary, ſuffered himſelf to be abus'd and miſled by evil Counſellors, to the great prejudice and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet of the Realm: For which cauſe (after he had Reigned 22 years) he was alſo depos'd by Act of Parliament held at <hi>London</hi> 1399, and condemn'd to perpetual Impriſonment in the Caſtle of <hi>Pomfret,</hi> where he was ſoon after put do death, as the other before had been; in whoſe place (by free Election) was choſen the Noble <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> who prov'd a notable King, and was Father to <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>5th,</hi> commonly call'd the <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> for as <hi>Alexander</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> conquered moſt part of <hi>Aſia</hi> in the ſpace of 9 or 10 years, ſo did this <hi>Henry</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer <hi>France</hi> in leſs time.</p>
            <p>I may alſo reckon in the number of Princes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd for defect in Government (thô otherwiſe of no ill life) <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>6th,</hi> who after 40 years Reign was depoſed and impriſoned by <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>4th</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>York;</hi> and the ſame was confirm'd by the Commons, and eſpecially by the People of <hi>London,</hi> and alſo by publick Act of Parliament; not only in reſpect of the Title which King <hi>Edward</hi> pretended, but alſo by reaſon that King <hi>Henry</hi> ſuffered himſelf to be over rul'd by the Queen his Wife, and had broken the Articles of Agreement made by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:63101:36"/>between him and the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſworn on both ſides; in puniſhment whereof and of his other negligent and evil Government, Sentence was given againſt him, and <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>4th</hi> elected in his place, who was an excellent Prince.</p>
            <p>But after this there ſell another Accident much more notorious, which was, That <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> this King <hi>Edward</hi>'s Brother, did put to death his two Nephews, and made himſelf King; and thô he acted very barbarouſly by taking the Crown in this wicked manner, yet when his Nephews were once dead, he might reaſonably ſeem to be lawful King, both in reſpect that he was next Mále after his Brother; as alſo, becauſe his Title was authoriz'd and made good by many Acts of Parliament, both before and after the deaths of thoſe Infants; and yet (I think) no man will ſay but that <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Richmond</hi> had very good reaſon to come out of <hi>France,</hi> being Called and Invited by the People of <hi>England</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge the Cruelties and Arbitrary things done by <hi>Richard</hi> the <hi>3d;</hi> and that this undertaking was no leſs ſucceſsful than generous, and obtain'd the Crown for his pains, after that <hi>Richard</hi> had died in the Field, and became King by the name of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>7th;</hi> and no man (I ſuppoſe) will deny him to have been a true and lawful King. And moreover, as I ſaid before, I would have you conſider in all theſe mutations, what Kings always ſucceeded in the places of ſuch as have been depos'd, as namely in <hi>England,</hi> in the place of thoſe Five Kings before-mentioned <hi>viz. John, Edward</hi> the <hi>2d, Richard</hi> the <hi>2d, Henry</hi> the <hi>6th,</hi> and <hi>Richard</hi> the <hi>3d,</hi> there have ſucceeded three <hi>Henries,</hi> the <hi>3d, 4th,</hi> and <hi>7th,</hi> and 2 <hi>Edwards,</hi> the <hi>3d</hi> and <hi>4th</hi> ſome of them moſt rare and valiant Princes who have done many im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Acts in their Commonwealth; and among
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:63101:36"/>others have raiſed many Houſes to the Nobility, put down others, changed States both abroad and at home, diſtributed Eccleſiaſtical Dignities, altered the courſe of Deſcent in the Royal Blood, and the like; all which was unjuſt, and is void at this day, if the Changes and Deprivations of the former Princes were not lawful; and conſequently King <hi>James</hi> the <hi>6th</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> nor any of his Deſcendents, had Title to this Crown, becauſe they deſcend from thoſe Kings who were elected in place of the deprived. And this I take to be a ſufficient proof, <hi>That lawful Kings have many times been lawfully depoſed by the States of the Kingdom, for Miſgovernment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I ſuppoſe it will be readily granted, That this ample Authority has been actually exerciſed by the aforeſaid Commonwealths againſt their evil Princes: but yet many perhaps will ask <hi>Quo jure,</hi> by what Law or Right? I anſwer, By all Laws both Divine and Human: <hi>Divine,</hi> by that Form of Government which every Kingdom doth chuſe unto it ſelf, as alſo the Conditions, Statutes and Limitations which it ſhall appoint to their Princes, as largely before hath been declared: And by <hi>Human Law</hi> alſo; being all Law, both Natural, National and Poſitive declares, That Princes are obliged to govern by Law and Order: For if they ſhould be bound to no Rules of Juſtice, but muſt be obeyed, be their Commands never ſo illegal and wicked then is the end of all Royal Government and Authority utterly defeated and uſeleſs; then may we ſubmit to all the Injuſtice and Arbitrary Commands that can be given to publick Murderers, Raviſhers, Thieves and Spoilers, to devour us; for ſuch indeed are they who follow no Law, but Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Senſuality, committing Injuſtice by their publick Authority.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:63101:37"/>
            <p>And finally, (which is the chiefeſt Reaſon of all and the very ground and foundation of all Kingly Authority among Chriſtians) the Power and Authority which the Prince hath from the Commonwealth is not abſolute, but a Power delegate, or Power of Truſt delegated by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from the People, which is given with ſuch Reſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, Limitations and Conditions, even with ſuch plain Promiſes and Oaths of both parties, (I mean between the King and Peo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le at the day of Admiſſion or Coronation) as if the ſame be not kept, but wilfully broken on either part, then is the other not bound to obſerve his Promiſe, tho' never ſo ſolemnly made or ſworn; for that in all Bargains, Agreements and Contracts, where each part is mutually and reciprocally bound to the other, by Oath, Vow or Condition, there if one party break his Promiſe, the other is not obliged to perform. And this is ſo evident by all Law, both of Nature and Nations, and ſo conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to all Reaſon and Equity, that it's inſerted among the very Rules of both the Civil and Law of Nations, where it's ſaid, <hi>Fruſtra fidem ſibi quis poſtulat ſervari ab co, cui fidem à ſe praeſtitam ſervare recuſat;</hi> He doth in vain require a Promiſe to be kept to him by another, to whom he refuſeth to perform that which himſelf promiſed. And again, <hi>Non aſtringitur quis Jaramento adimplendum, quod juravit, ſi ab alia parte non impletur, cujus reſpectu prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit Juramentum;</hi> A man is not bound to perform that which by Oath he promiſed, if on the other part that be not performed, in reſpect whereof his Oath was made. As for Example, if two ſhould ſwear to aſſiſt each other upon the way in all reſpects, and after falling upon Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies who were Relations of Friends to one of them, and he ſhould take their part againſt his Companion, its clear that the other was not bound to keep his Oath to that Man, that had ſo wickedly broken his to him: Nay, not only in this caſe, that is ſo evident by Nature it ſelf, but in many others alſo, it is both lawful, honeſt and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, to leave ſometimes the performance of our Oath, when by fulfilling it, there would accrue any notable Inconveniences againſt Religion, Piety, Juſtice, Honeſty, or the weal-publick, or againſt the party himſelf to whom
<pb facs="tcp:63101:37"/>it was made. As if one had ſworn to reſtore a Sword to a mad or furious Man, wherewith it were likely he would deſtroy himſelf or others; and ſuch like caſes, which <hi>Cicero</hi> ſets down in his firſt <hi>Book of Offices,</hi> and deduces them from the very ground of Nature, and Reaſon it ſelf, and ſays, that it were againſt the duty of a good or honeſt Man, it ſuch caſes to perform his Promiſe. Our Divines alſo do alledge the Example of <hi>Herod,</hi> who had ſworn to the Daughter of <hi>Herodias,</hi> to give her what ſhe demanded, who demanded the Head of S. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> thô <hi>Herod</hi> was ſorry for it; yet ſaith the Text, <hi>For his Oaths ſake he commanded it to be performed;</hi> which yet no man will deny, but that it had been far better left unperformed, according to the Rule of Law, <hi>In malis promiſſis fidem non expedit-obſervare,</hi> It is not expedient to keep our Oath when unlawfully made. And in the ſecond Part of the <hi>Decretal</hi> there's alledged this Sentence out of <hi>Iſidorus,</hi> and eſtabliſh'd for Law, <hi>In malis promiſſis reſcinde fidem, in turpi voto muta decretum, impia enim promiſſio quae ſcelere impletur;</hi> In evil Promiſes perform not your word, in an unlawful Vow or Oath change your determination; for its an impious Promiſe that cannot be fulfill'd, but with Wickedneſs. So as nothing is more largely handled both in the Civil and Canon Law, than this matter of Promiſes, how and when, and in what caſe they hold or bind, and when not.</p>
            <p>All which to apply to our matter of Kings; We are to underſtand that two evident Caſes are touched here, when a Subjects Oath or Promiſe of Obedience may be left unperform'd to his Prince: The firſt, when the Prince obſerves not the Promiſe or Oath made to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth at his Admiſſion or Coronation; the ſecond, when it ſhould turn to the great damage of the Weal publick, (for whoſe ſake only good Princes were ordain'd as often before hath been ſaid and proved) if the Subject ſhould keep his Promiſe and Oath made unto him. For if in my Opinion he is an Enemy to the Truth, and that his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion obliges him in Conſcience to deſtroy and extirpate all that are not of it, ſhall act againſt my Conſcience and ſin damnably in the ſight of God, if I do not endeavour
<pb facs="tcp:63101:38"/>to render him incapable of deſtroying others that are not of his own erroneous Opinion, and of bringing their to perdition, wherein I am perſwaded he remains. This Doctrin is founded upon the diſcourſe of S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Corinthians,</hi> againſt ſuch Chriſtians as were invited to the Banquets and Tables of <hi>Gentiles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 14. Cor. 10.14.</note> and finding Meats offered to Idols (which they eſteemed unlawful to eat) did yet eat the ſame againſt their own Judgment and Conſcience, which the Apoſtle ſaith was a <hi>damnable Sin;</hi> not becauſe the thing it ſelf was evil or unlawful, but becauſe they judg'd it ſo and yet did it.</p>
            <p>And now to apply all this to our preſent purpoſe, affirm and hold, That for any man to give his help, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or aſſiſtance to the making or upholding of a King whom he believes to be of a wrong Religion, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to root out and extirpate thoſe he thinks Hereticks, and who conſequently will endeavour all he can to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote it and ruin ours, our Liberties, Propertie; and what elſe is valuable to us, is a moſt grievous and damnable Sin For if S. <hi>Paul</hi> has plainly and abſolutely pronounc'd in the place before alledged, that even in eating a piece of Meat that its damnable for a man to diſcern and yet eat: What may we think will it be in ſo great and important: matter as he making of King if, for a man to diſſemble or act againſt his own Conſcience or Judgment? that is to ſay, to diſcern and judge that he's a declared Enemy of our Religion, and obliged t deſtroy the Profeſſors o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it; and yet to further or uphold his Authority and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment over Proteſtants, where he may be able to ruin or pervert many, and to obſtruct all Honour and true Worſhip due to God? and whether he does this or not yet I ſhall be guilty of it all; for that knowing and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading my ſelf, that he is like or diſpoſed to do it by the Principles of his Religion, yet for fear, ſlattery, careleſneſs, emulation againſt others, vain pretence of Title, want o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Zeal to Gods true Religion and Worſhip, or for ſuch other paſſions or temporal reſpects, I favour or further his Pretences, or do not reſiſt him when it's in my power, by which I do juſtly make my ſelf guilty of all the Evils, Miſeries and Calamities both Temporal and Spiritual,
<pb facs="tcp:63101:38"/>which afterwards by his evil Government do, or may enſure, for that I knowing him to be ſuch an one, did notwithſtanding aſſiſt his promotion. And thus much for matter of Conſcience.</p>
            <p>But if we reſpect Reaſon of State alſo and Worldly Policy, it muſt be great folly and overſight for a man to promote to a Kingdom; in which he muſt live, one of ſo pernicious and deſtructive Religion to himſelf; for let the Bargains and Agreements be what they will, and fair Promiſes and vain Hopes never ſo great, yet ſeeing the Prince once made and ſetled, muſt needs proceed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Principles of that Religion, and conſequently muſt ſoon break with the other Party, thô before he loved him never ſo well, (which perhaps is very hard, if not impoſſible, for two of ſo oppoſite Religions to love ſincerely;) but if it were ſo, many ſuſpicions, accuſations, calumniations and other averſions muſt needs light on the Party, who is of ſo oppoſite and different Religion from his King, as not only he cannot be capable of ſuch preferments and honours which he may deſire and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in his Country, but alſo he ſhall be in continual danger, and ſubject to a thouſand Moleſtations and Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, always incident to thoſe men who are not currant with the courſe of their Prince in matters of Religion: Which to remedy, they muſt either diſſemble deeply, and againſt their own Conſcience pretend to favour and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Deſigns of the Government, how pernicious ſoever they may be to the welfare of the Kingdom; or elſe to avoid this ſlaviſh diſſimulation, they muſt wave all the temporal Commodities of this life, and leave the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits which their Country might afford them, and live Exiles in a forein Kingdom; which has been the fate of many brave Men in our time: So as of all the diſabilities which ſerve to exclude or remove a Prince, the adhering to ſo deſtructive and pernicious a Religion as <hi>Popery</hi> is, is the principle, and ought to be the firſt and chiefeſt thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd by the Commonwealth; eſpecially he being of that Religion which denies all charity, peace, happineſs, or ſecurity of Life or Property to ſuch as are not of its Communion; whoſe growth and increaſe the State hath
<pb facs="tcp:63101:39"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>nicious a Doctrin, which notwithſtanding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> uſeleſs and ineffectual for our ſecurity, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>James,</hi> a proteſt Papiſt, was admitted to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, who with one breath ſuſpended and annull'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Laws of the Reformation. And thô we have been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uilty of great overſight and failure, and been wanting to the ſecurity and ſupport of the true Proteſtant Religion, when he was but Heir apparent, and (as I ſaid before) a Spouſe betrothed only, and not married to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; yet (to purſue the Allegory) we have made as good reparation, as ſuch an overſight could permit, by divorc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, and taking a new Husband of our Perſwaſion.</p>
            <p>Now S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> determines plainly, That if two Gentils married together in their Gentility (which none can deny to be a true Marriage for ſo much as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the Civil Contract) and after one is made a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, the other will not live with him or her; or if he do, nor without blaſpheming God and temptation to Sin: In this caſe (I ſay) the Apoſtle teacheth and out of him the Canon Law decrees, that this is ſufficient to break and diſſolve utterly this Heathen Marriage, and that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian may marry again, and this only for want of Religion in the other party, which being ſo in an actual Marriage, which is ſo much favoured by Chriſt, when he ſaid, <hi>Whom God hath joyned, let no man ſeparate;</hi> it is much cleaver in this Metaphorical Marriage of a King to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, which may be diſſolved for many more Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and with infinite leſs danger of incurring Gods An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than the former: So that I hope all ingenuous Readers who peruſe this Treatiſe, and throughly weigh and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Examples and Arguments herein mentioned, will think themſelves free from all obligations of Duty or Allegiance to the late King <hi>James,</hi> being his Authority is expired, to which Allegiance, was inſeparably incident, and ſeated in the Royal Perſons of <hi>Willian</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> our moſt renowned King and Queen, whom we are bound to obey without the leaſt ſcruple.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
